<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Psychology | Dr Dominique Makowski</title>
    <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/psychology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Psychology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/media/icon_hu1b87c1310da332ba1b18c001e4f10dac_153312_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Psychology</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/psychology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is neuropsychology?</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-13-what_is_neuropsychology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-13-what_is_neuropsychology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-place-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The place of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make a simple experiment&lt;/strong&gt;. Pick one young and brilliant neuropsychologist and ask &amp;ldquo;what is neuropsychology?&amp;rdquo;. In some cases, after a few seconds of hesitation, you could hear answers like &amp;ldquo;being a neuropsychologist means doing &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. In other cases, you might come across incomplete - or even false - responses, such as &amp;ldquo;neuropsychology is a tool&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a method&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a paradigm&amp;rdquo;, or even worse, &amp;ldquo;a point of view&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does not mean that our neuropsychologist is incompetent, far from it. But formally defining our field as a whole is not an exercise that we are used to do. Indeed, &lt;strong&gt;the training in neuropsychology usually comes in a fragmented way&lt;/strong&gt;, little by little. &lt;em&gt;A bit of cognitive neuroscience here, a bit of neuropsychological syndromes there, some cognitive tests administration over here, and some cortical neuroanatomy over there&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; Though we might, &lt;em&gt;in fine&lt;/em&gt;, acquire a global vision and understanding of neuropsychology, verbalizing it is seldom necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of neuropsychology is actually quite complex to formalize, and can even be hotly debated. The jobs and positions that stem out of this field are many, and &lt;strong&gt;practitioners often tend to circumscribe neuropsychology to their own activity&lt;/strong&gt;. For instance, a neuropsychologist that mainly does cognitive rehabilitation with psychiatric patients might have quite a different vision from another that does, day after day, presurgical cognitive assessments. And that is without mentioning the neuropsychologists pursuing an academic career, or even the ones that have moved to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No problem&lt;/em&gt;, would argue the careful reader, &lt;em&gt;if the definitions are too narrow, let&amp;rsquo;s take more general one&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Indeed, neuropsychology occupies a very particular place in the network of science, as it is at &lt;strong&gt;the crossroads between social sciences, biological sciences and medical fields&lt;/strong&gt;. Giving a definition that is too large would lose its essence in the nebulous depths of neuroscience and psychology, which would be not be accurate; neuropsychologists, whether they are clinical practitioners or not, have a common training, a specific theoretical grounding, as well as a unique interpretation and analysis framework underpinned by a scientifically rigorous method. Taking these elements into account, I will attempt to give a &lt;strong&gt;simple, comprehensive and informative definition of neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first axiom that we need to discuss is the notion of science. &lt;strong&gt;Is neuropsychology its &amp;ldquo;own&amp;rdquo; scientific field&lt;/strong&gt;, or is it a mere portion of another one, such as cognitive neuroscience or psychology, which differs from other specializations only through its object of interest? &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;By science&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, says Schopenhauer in his PhD thesis with a baroque title (On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason), &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we understand a system of notions, i.e. a totality of connected, as opposed to a mere aggregate of disconnected, notions.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; This definition applies well to neuropsychology, that contains a set of theories, hypotheses, methods and proofs feeding from one another and creating a coherent ensemble. As such, neuropsychology is its own scientific discipline, although a singular one&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, &lt;strong&gt;what is the &amp;ldquo;bigger&amp;rdquo; box in which neuropsychology fits?&lt;/strong&gt; While neuropsychologists are often initially trained in psychology, one could argue that the focus on the brain makes it more belonging to neuroscience. Well, the organization and structure of Science is a complicated issue. However, the particularity of the topographical location of neuropsychology is quite apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, neuropsychology belongs to a cluster of sciences interested a specific biological organ: the brain. As such, &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology is an integral part of neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt;. On the other hand, neuropsychology is interested in the productions of the brain (e.g., thoughts, feelings and behaviours) with a focus on the cognitive level (analyzing things in terms of cognitive processes and mechanisms), which makes it also &lt;strong&gt;belonging to psychology&lt;/strong&gt;. Moreover, one could argue that neuropsychology, through its integration of the study of what we are biologically, and who we are mentally, has been connected to, and used as evidence in, &lt;strong&gt;philosophy of mind&lt;/strong&gt; debates (for instance, famous neuropsychological cases studied by Sacks, Ramachandran or Milner have been widely discussed by contemporary philosophers). Finally, contrary to many other domains, neuropsychology has also an applied, practical component, that can be used in clinical practice. This clinical aspect, registering &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology withing medical fields&lt;/strong&gt;, takes multiple forms, such as assessment, diagnostic or therapeutic care, and can be used with a wide variety of patients and illnesses. These multiple facets make the wealth of &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology, which offers an exceptional freedom of practice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology is located at the centre of colliding galaxies of knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, such as neuroscience, psychology, medicine and philosophy. However, the fast development of neuropsychology is gradually leading to the creation of subcomponents within itself, corresponding to different practices and theoretical steps. And these clusters are themselves growing. For instance, clinical neuropsychology was historically focused on diagnostic cognitive assessments, but has recently expanded on the treatment-side of things, with innovations like cognitive training and rehabilitation. This underlines neuropsychology as a rapidly evolving field, moving its potential towards yet uncharted territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourfold-structure-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The fourfold structure of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuropsychology is born from the convergence of &lt;strong&gt;cognitive neurology&lt;/strong&gt;, with pioneers such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Broca&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Broca&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Wernicke&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wernicke&lt;/a&gt; (which made inferences about brain functioning based on the observations of patients with brain lesions) and psychologists such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Th%C3%A9odule-Armand_Ribot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ribot&lt;/a&gt; (focusing on the organization and semiology of cognitive deficits). This history has shaped neuropsychology as a two-faced entity, with one &lt;strong&gt;experimental side&lt;/strong&gt; dedicated to understand the relationship between brain and cognition (by using pathological cases or natural variability of neurocognitive characteristics), and one &lt;strong&gt;clinical aspect&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on bringing this knowledge to the benefit of the patients suffering from brain disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, beyond these two pillars of neuropsychology, recent advances have outlined a more &lt;strong&gt;theoretical level&lt;/strong&gt; of neuropsychology, dedicated to a high-level integration of the data at hand to elaborate general theories and interfacing them with evolutionary or philosophical principles. Similarly, a &lt;strong&gt;computational&lt;/strong&gt; facet, referring to the operationalization of the functioning in statistical terms, starts to emerge as a pseudo-independent aspect, propelled by the regain of interest and focus on the methodological and statistical aspects of psychology and neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This structure is not fixed, but driven by the evolution of the field. It is possible that new poles will emerge, or differentiate over time, until maybe they separate from - or create new clusters within - neuropsychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;cycle.png&#34; alt=&#34;Structure of neuropsychology&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The fourfold structure of neuropsychology.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-definition-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The definition of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuropsychology is a theoretical and practical science investigating the relationship between 1) the structure and functioning of the brain, and 2) cognitive processes and their related derivatives, such as thoughts, feelings and behaviours.&lt;/strong&gt; It is organised in four interconnected and overlapping dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; studies the variability of the brain and cognition (whether from pathological origin or not) to test theories and models through empirical experimentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; uses theories and models about mental functioning to better detect and assess disorders and deficits, leading to a precise diagnostic and an adapted treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computational neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; transforms the data acquired through experiments and observation into logical or statistical models of mental functioning that are used to operationalize the processes at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theoretical neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; integrates the evidence to elaborate and develop unifying theories to address fundamental questions about mental functioning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuropsychology is located at the crossroads between neuroscience and psychology, at the interface between theory and practice. &lt;strong&gt;Its practitioners, the neuropsychologists&lt;/strong&gt;, are bound by a specific training, by unique theoretical and historical references, and are endowed with an analysis and interpretation framework backed by a rigorous and scientific investigation methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie expérimentale étudie les variabilités du cerveau et de la cognition (qu’elles soient d’origine pathologique ou non) pour tester des modèles et développer des théories sur le fonctionnement mental, visant ainsi à une meilleure compréhension de l’Homme. --&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie clinique utilise les théories et les modèles sur le fonctionnement mental pour mieux détecter et appréhender les troubles et les déficits d’une pathologie, menant à un diagnostic précis, tout en développant et appliquant des prises en charges modernes et adaptées. --&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie se situe au centre de la nébuleuse des neurosciences, au carrefour de la théorie et de la pratique. Ses praticiens, les neuropsychologues, sont liés par une formation commune, des bases théoriques spécifiques, un canevas d’analyse et d’interprétation sous-tendu par une méthode d’investigation rigoureuse et scientifique.  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post, and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicolas, S., &amp;amp; Murray, D. J. (1999). Théodule Ribot (1839–1916), founder of French psychology: A biographical introduction. History of Psychology, 2(4), 277.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schopenhauer, A. (1813). &lt;em&gt;On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason&lt;/em&gt;. PhD dissertation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;You can reference this post as follows:&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;- Makowski, D. (2020, September 13). What is Neuropsychology?. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/what_is_neuropsychology/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/what_is_neuropsychology/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why psychologists should join GitHub</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-05-27-github_psychologists/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-05-27-github_psychologists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything to do with GitHub, aside from being a simple user. This article is not an advertisement for it, but rather a perspective on the role of technical social networks in psychology.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/r_or_python/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;another post&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;strong&gt;technical aspects and skills will play an increasing role in psychology&lt;/strong&gt;. This relationship isn&amp;rsquo;t by any means new. More than a century ago, pioneering psychologists were demonstrating formidable engineering and craftsmanship skills to build new tools and apparatuses to measure what they were interested in (see for instance &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/publication/nicolas2016can/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nicolas &amp;amp; Makowski, 2016&lt;/a&gt;). But years have gone by, and the digital revolution has happened. As a result, most of the &amp;ldquo;technical&amp;rdquo; aspects (a rather vague term covering everything that is not related to the semantic knowledge of psychological theories and facts) are now ultimately tied to &lt;em&gt;software&lt;/em&gt;. Critically, &lt;strong&gt;your ability to use these softwares will determine the speed and ease at which you can achieve your goals and produce high quality assignments&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, during my studies, most of the statistics course was delivered through the usage of one particular software (Statistica© 🤮). At the exam, your score didn&amp;rsquo;t much depend on your understanding of what a &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt;-test is, when to use it or anything like that; but rather on your knowledge of the software, and your ability to &lt;strong&gt;click on the right buttons faster than your peers&lt;/strong&gt;. While this is an unfortunate example that can be used to criticize the reliance on tools rather than fundamental knowledge, it also tells us something about the reality of the current world. In research, the better you are for instance at data processing (which involves both the knowledge of how to navigate the software &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the knowledge of what to do in general), the faster you will be able to carry it out, and the less stressed you will be, resulting in a cascade of other positive outcomes (increased well-being, work-quality, productivity, opportunities, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;strong&gt;one common mistake is to delay learning&lt;/strong&gt; new stuff (especially things outside our comfort zone) until we have no choice. This is understandable given that in the short term, certain skills may not be absolutely needed (i.e., you can manage without them) and acquiring them can be a steep learning curve (which can be hard, frustrating and effortful). However, you should start investing in your technical skills as soon as possible (as the time devoted to learning will only shrink as you advance) if you don&amp;rsquo;t want to become very &lt;strong&gt;close friends with pressure, stress, hatred, frustration and despair&lt;/strong&gt;. So stay on the light side of the force and embrace the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;vader.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;github for psychologists&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A psychology researcher realizing that he should have learned programming earlier.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not just about learning to &lt;strong&gt;use&lt;/strong&gt; some software just for the sake of having things done and getting faster results. A lot of science is done &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt; software, not only &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; them. People are actively discussing new methods, algorithms and tools that then expand like never before the possibilities of researchers. &lt;strong&gt;Flaming debates have been going on with frameworks and workflows clashing with thunderous sparks&lt;/strong&gt; (for instance, Bayesian &lt;em&gt;vs.&lt;/em&gt; frequentist statistics, ANOVAs &lt;em&gt;vs.&lt;/em&gt; (mixed) regressions, etc.), and these calls for change find echo because of developments of software, allowing initiated users to test, validate and use new methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-access-software&#34;&gt;Open-access software&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might not seem like it when you&amp;rsquo;re studying it at the university, but science is currently in the middle of a &lt;strong&gt;revolution&lt;/strong&gt;. A massive paradigmatic change, partly fuelled by the growth of &lt;strong&gt;open-science&lt;/strong&gt;, which covers aspects like open-access and open-source. This means, for software, that they are no longer being developed by private companies and sold for money. Instead, they are developed in a public fashion, and &lt;strong&gt;everybody is welcome to chime in and provide input, suggestions, report bugs or improve the code&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source development means faster and better software, and more importantly, the creation of a &lt;strong&gt;true connection between developers and users&lt;/strong&gt;. In fact, the former are often first and foremost also the latter, meaning that in a lot of cases (at least, mine 😅), people started writing a software because they needed it for their own personal job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the beauty lies in the fact that &lt;strong&gt;users can seemingly become developers&lt;/strong&gt; too, or &lt;strong&gt;contributors&lt;/strong&gt;, at the very least. Sometimes, users end up on a software development page to solve a bug or an issue that they encountered. From there, there can start following the developments, and getting involved. And &lt;strong&gt;not necessarily be writing code&lt;/strong&gt;. It can be by answering to other issues, helping other users, reporting bugs and typos, improving the documentation, giving ideas and suggestions, testing new features and encouraging the developers. There are so many to contribute to the development and, as a result, become an active member of the open-science community. And moreover, doing so is also a great way to learn the theoretical bits. For instance, the most efficient way of learning the complexities of EEG acquisition and processing was to follow the development of an EEG-processing software (namely, &lt;a href=&#34;https://mne.tools/stable/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;MNE-Python&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). Reading issues that users encountered, and replies from experts and developers, trying to understand what functions do, what are the different parameters, what are the possibilities, the limits and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, engaging in open-source software is a great way to increase your technical expertise and get involved in the community of researchers. And who knows, you might meet cool people, create new connections, and that&amp;rsquo;s always great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;expectations.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;open source software expectations&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Help making the first pane true.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;software-as-a-social-network&#34;&gt;Software as a social network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you&amp;rsquo;ve buckled up, ready to engage in open-source software, you might wonder; &lt;strong&gt;where does that happen?&lt;/strong&gt; Ladies and gentlemen, let me introduce &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/neuropsychology/NeuroKit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, when I was an undergrad student, I had to write a lot of stuff, such as for instance reports, project and theses. All of these documents went through several back and forths with supervisors, which made comments and modifications. But I was terribly afraid to remove some paragraph or sentence that I would need later on. As a result, I ended up in a hell in which my tormentors were named &lt;code&gt;project.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v2.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v3.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v3_modifs.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v3_final.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v4_comments.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v4_final.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v4final2.docx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;project_v4_finalfinal.docx&lt;/code&gt;. And what if my computer broke &lt;sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;(that was before Dropbox)&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;? I could lose everything 😱&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when I heard about something called &lt;strong&gt;version control&lt;/strong&gt;. Apparently, there was a system out there that allowed you to save &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; your modifications, and be able to go back at &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; point in time. This system was called &lt;em&gt;git&lt;/em&gt;, and it was super obscure. However, I discovered that this system had a, online interface, in the form of a website, on which you can go and upload files and documents for free. This is how &lt;strong&gt;I discovered GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;. And back in the days, it was really mostly used by programmers (because the nature of code makes it very suited for &lt;em&gt;version control&lt;/em&gt;), a world I didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    There several great alternatives go &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt;, like &lt;em&gt;GitLab&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;BitBucket&lt;/em&gt;, etc., that might be just as good, if not better. The reason why I&amp;rsquo;m mainly talking about &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; here is because this post is not about the intrinsic quality or features of these platforms &lt;em&gt;for developers&lt;/em&gt;, but rather as a social network. An important part of any social network is its popularity and - as of for now - &lt;em&gt;GitHub&lt;/em&gt; is the most popular.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I witnessed &lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt; growing and becoming a true &lt;em&gt;social network&lt;/em&gt;, improving its accessibility and user-friendliness. It is now more like a hub where all kinds of people gather to discuss software and technical bits, than a den for hairy geeks. There are also many users who are new to programming (e.g. researchers who are using software as a means to an end) and if you belong to this category of people, don&amp;rsquo;t underestimate your contribution to developers! Often it is such users that help developers improve user friendliness and identify code bugs (for example, when running the code on actual data sets). It is also used as a public technical portfolio, in which you can display your achievements, your projects and your interests. And while it was originally centred around programming, it has extended its audience quite a bit, and people are now using GitHub to store data (for instance the COVID-19 data), books, create websites (for instance, this website is stored on GitHub) or write scientific papers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason why I&amp;rsquo;m writing this is because I know all too many young researchers, grappling with some software, struggling to find help, that are too shy to just contact the developers or the community. Just jump in there, create a public issue (instead of writing an email, so that your question will benefit future users). Most of the developers will be happy to help, and glad to see their software and code actually used by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, go and dive into the world of open-science and open-source software, you&amp;rsquo;ll be on the right side of history. 😎&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-to-do-once-youre-on-github&#34;&gt;What to do once you&amp;rsquo;re on GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the very least, the very first step is to create an account. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t use it now, it will be useful in the future (it shows that you are interested in technical stuff, it allows you to post issues and connect to other platforms, and support developers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find&lt;/strong&gt; a package / software that you like. Super biased suggestions include:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/neuropsychology/NeuroKit&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;NeuroKit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: a Python package for Neurophysiological Signal Processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/easystats/bayestestR&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;bayestestR&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: an R package for Bayesian statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/easystats/correlation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;correlation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: an R package for correlations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/easystats/report&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;report&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: an R package to report statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/easystats/effectsize&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;effectsize&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: an R package for effect sizes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/easystats/parameters&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;parameters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: an R package for understanding statistical models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/easystats/performance&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;performance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: an R package for testing how good your model is&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Watch it&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo; (the button in the top-right corner), so you&amp;rsquo;ll be notified of its activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read&lt;/strong&gt; the README file (the &amp;ldquo;front page&amp;rdquo;), check-out the issues, understand how to navigate the repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage&lt;/strong&gt; with the developers, create an issue to report bugs or problems, or just to express support - developing a software takes time and effort, and is often done out of passion and for free. Words of encouragement are always appreciated 🤗&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; your own &lt;a href=&#34;https://guides.github.com/activities/hello-world/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;repository&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make&lt;/strong&gt; your own &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;website&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you want to learn how to use &lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt; to make contributions, check-out our &lt;a href=&#34;https://neurokit2.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorials/contributing.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tutorial&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Let me know if I forgot something by adding a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 👇&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R or Python for Psychologists</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-05-22-r_or_python/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-05-22-r_or_python/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many psychology students or researchers are faced with the challenge - &lt;em&gt;or the opportunity&lt;/em&gt; - of learning a programming language. &lt;strong&gt;Which one should you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an ex- psych student and a daily user and developer of both, here&amp;rsquo;s my take on this hot debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-has-programming-to-do-with-psychology&#34;&gt;What has programming to do with psychology?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a very young psychology student, or a future one, you might wonder: &lt;strong&gt;why the heck would I have to learn programming in psychology?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Psychology is like philosophy, it&amp;rsquo;s just learning how people&amp;rsquo;s minds work by reading books and overthinking stuff&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. If you still think that, you&amp;rsquo;re in for &lt;strong&gt;one hell of a ride&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychology is, since its very beginning, a hard and experimental science. The founding fathers of psychology were dedicated to find ways to objectively &lt;em&gt;measure&lt;/em&gt; psychological phenomena and uncovering the mathematical laws that govern Human behaviour (one of the fields of psychology is even called psycho&lt;em&gt;physics&lt;/em&gt;). This &lt;em&gt;sciency&lt;/em&gt; nature has been toned down by the booming popularity of &lt;strong&gt;pseudo-scientific approaches like psychoanalysis&lt;/strong&gt;, that contributed to the stereotypical public image of the shrink doodling while listening to a neurotic patient. But that&amp;rsquo;s a distorted and old-fashioned view, clearly not representative of the future of psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact is that psychology is very closely connected with &lt;strong&gt;statistics&lt;/strong&gt;. Many great statistical advances were made by psychologists, and all true psychological discoveries are backed by statistical findings. And this importance of statistics is - and will be - growing further, partly due to the recent realization of some major issues in the field due to improper statistical procedures (coined the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Replication_crisis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;replicability crisis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;). Moreover, psychology is more and more relying on advanced data-acquiring methods (smartphone apps, website data, physiological and brain recording devices like EEG, MRI, etc.). And these new formats often require specialized knowledge (web-scraping, database querying, neuroimaging, signal processing, machine learning, &amp;hellip;). Even in the most applied kind of &lt;strong&gt;clinical&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;psychotherapeutic&lt;/strong&gt; specialization, where you&amp;rsquo;d think you&amp;rsquo;d be safe, they are starting to use data intensive methods like neuro-feedback, virtual reality or smartphone sensing and surveying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long story short, no matter which branch of psychology you specialize in, you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be confronted with some technical aspects that won&amp;rsquo;t be able to solve with &lt;em&gt;Excel&lt;/em&gt;. Importantly, these are the skills that will make the most difference between students, and that will matter a lot if you want to pursue research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, &lt;strong&gt;ready to dive into programming?&lt;/strong&gt; Fear not! It&amp;rsquo;s not that complicated. Moreover, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;one of the most rewarding skill&lt;/strong&gt; you can develop. I can assure you that you won&amp;rsquo;t regret the time invested in learning it 😊&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But where should you start?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-r-and-python&#34;&gt;Both R and Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This increasing relationship between psychology and statistics on the one hand, and other more general technical aspects on the other, is the reason why R and Python are so popular in psychology. Both languages are &lt;strong&gt;free&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;open-source&lt;/strong&gt;, suited for &lt;strong&gt;beginners&lt;/strong&gt;, and have a large base of users with a ton of &lt;strong&gt;learning material&lt;/strong&gt; online. What&amp;rsquo;s the difference between them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put simply, &lt;strong&gt;R is for statistics, Python is for the rest&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why is there a virulent debate going on, and a choice to make? It&amp;rsquo;s true that I, &lt;em&gt;in theory&lt;/em&gt;, would recommend &lt;strong&gt;learning both&lt;/strong&gt;, as they are complementary and have their own strengths and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, many opinionated people arguing in favour of one &lt;strong&gt;or&lt;/strong&gt; the other (usually the only one they know) will say that learning both is essentially a waste of time. They will put forth a strong argument: &lt;strong&gt;you can do whatever you do in R in Python, and &lt;em&gt;vice-versa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In other words, both languages can be used to achieve your goals, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;better to specialize in one than have a limited knowledge of both&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I do not agree with that statement, I do acknowledge that people have limited time and resources to learn. Saying &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;just learn both&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; is easy, but is arguably an unrealistic expectation for the vast majority of people. So why learning both can be a long-term goal (especially if you want to do research), you have to start somewhere. So, &lt;strong&gt;what starter language should you select?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;pokemon.png&#34; alt=&#34;r or python&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Ash choosing his starter programming language. He has the choice between R, Python and Bulbasaur, i.e, Matlab - the one that no one likes.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-matlab&#34;&gt;What about Matlab?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a time when &lt;em&gt;Matlab&lt;/em&gt; was the boss. It was used everywhere and had the best functionalities for neuroimaging, signal processing and maths. But &lt;strong&gt;that time is over&lt;/strong&gt;. Matlab is already a dead language, which burial process will continue in the years to come. Why is it dead? Because it is &lt;strong&gt;expensive&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;closed&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;ugly&lt;/strong&gt;, and most importantly the alternatives (namely R and Python) are now more powerful and featured than Matlab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://media.giphy.com/media/sDOhzJBsFvjMY/giphy.gif&#34; alt=&#34;matlab&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Agamemnon reacting to king Priam saying &#34;The city of Matlab will never be conquered&#34;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is, there are only two reasons people still use Matlab: &lt;strong&gt;habit&lt;/strong&gt; (it&amp;rsquo;s hard to learn a new approach if your old way of doing things still works) and &lt;strong&gt;SPM&lt;/strong&gt; (a toolbox for neuroimaging that is still - &lt;em&gt;for now&lt;/em&gt; - the leader in the field).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But seriously, don&amp;rsquo;t waste time on it if you have limited resources, it&amp;rsquo;s just not worth it. You will learn an outdated tool that you won&amp;rsquo;t be able to use in another lab if they don&amp;rsquo;t agree to pay for an expensive license (unless you&amp;rsquo;re a pirate ☠️). Whereas with open and free languages like R or Python, you have access to the best tools and can use them freely everywhere. Also, it makes you a &lt;strong&gt;supporter of open-science&lt;/strong&gt;, and that&amp;rsquo;s trendy 😁.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-decide-between-r-and-python&#34;&gt;How to decide between R and Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time has come to make a decision.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite what people say, &lt;strong&gt;R and Python are not equivalent&lt;/strong&gt;. You can argue as much as you want, but doing statistics and data visualization in Python is not as fast, easy and neat as it is in R. And signal processing or neuroimaging is not as powerful in R as compared to Python. Note that both languages are still growing and changing, and they are influencing themselves: for instance, many popular Python modules (e.g., &lt;strong&gt;pandas&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;statsmodels&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;seaborn&lt;/strong&gt;, &amp;hellip;) have been directly inspired by R. As such, the boundaries between the two languages are fading (and I&amp;rsquo;m not even mentioning the great advances in interoperability, with tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.github.io/reticulate/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;reticulate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that allow you to use one language directly inside the other).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, Python and R remain very different languages at their core, with a different feel and vibe to it. R was made by statisticians for statistics, and the majority of its users are academics and researchers. On the contrary, Python is a true general-purpose &amp;ldquo;programming&amp;rdquo; language, widely used outside of academia, in the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some things to consider when deciding on what language to learn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reasons-to-choose-python&#34;&gt;Reasons to choose Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have some basic knowledge or familiarity with programming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, you know what a loop is. Python being a true programming language, having any prior experience will be useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are good with logic and spatial representation (like imagining shapes in 3D, rotating them, etc.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python, you will have to think with a &amp;ldquo;programming&amp;rdquo; mindset. That means perceiving things in terms of logical statements and blocks, understanding data as 2D or 3D tables that you have to slice and recombine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are comfortable with maths&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python, numbers and numbers combinations are used a lot. Paradoxically, you will typically see a lot more of maths in Python than in R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You plan to do signal processing or experimental tasks creation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some of the domains where Python is well-established (which doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that R doesn&amp;rsquo;t have some great tools in development).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are good at googling and don&amp;rsquo;t mind spending time looking for the right answer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python has so much material online that it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes hard to find the appropriate thing. Harder than in R, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reasons-to-choose-r&#34;&gt;Reasons to choose R&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have no experience with programming whatsoever&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R is not made to be used as a traditional &lt;em&gt;programming&lt;/em&gt; language. It&amp;rsquo;s more of finding what functions to apply to what, and that makes it easy for beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are interested in statistical analyses, modelling things, and making inferences from data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R excels at this. You can create powerful models super easily and jump into their understanding and interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You like making nice figures and plots&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;R, through the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ggplot2.tidyverse.org/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ggplot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ecosystem, has hands down the best tools for visualization. Your imagination is the limit (check-out the artworks by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.data-imaginist.com/art&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Thomas Lin Pedersen&lt;/a&gt; abd &lt;a href=&#34;https://art.djnavarro.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Danielle Navarro&lt;/a&gt; 😍).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; so good with stats or maths&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You heard it right! To start with R you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know stats or maths like a boss. R, in fact, will help you to become proficient at it, by slowly opening more and more layers of complexity to you, if you are deemed worthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You are interested in joining the academic community&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because most of its users are academics, R has a fantastic community online, for instance on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/rstats&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Twitter #rstats&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-considerations&#34;&gt;Other considerations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What your peers are learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easier to learn together, so try to discuss it with your class or lab mates if you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What your lab is using&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might be easier if you have mentors that can understand what you are doing and guide you. But that should not be a priority, as it can lead to old habits reproduction (especially if your lab has a tradition of Matlab 🤭).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hands-on&#34;&gt;Hands on!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👉 Looking for places to start? Check out this &lt;a href=&#34;https://neurokit2.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorials/learnpython.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10-min crash course introduction to Python&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and this &lt;a href=&#34;https://easystats.github.io/blog/resources/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;collection of resources for R&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;em&gt;and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 👇&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
