<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Reality Bending Lab | Dr Dominique Makowski</title>
    <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/category/reality-bending-lab/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/category/reality-bending-lab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Reality Bending Lab</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/media/icon_hu1b87c1310da332ba1b18c001e4f10dac_153312_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Reality Bending Lab</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/category/reality-bending-lab/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>New location and new logo!</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-02-01-new_logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-02-01-new_logo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New year, new start. And as I am officially starting a new faculty position at the &lt;strong&gt;University of Sussex&lt;/strong&gt; in Brighton, UK, the lab is moving too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a bit of perspective, we started as the &amp;ldquo;Reality Bending League&amp;rdquo;, which was the unofficial name of the team working with me (&amp;ldquo;League&amp;rdquo; was chosen to keep the lab&amp;rsquo;s acronym, &lt;strong&gt;ReBeL&lt;/strong&gt;). It then became a semi-official group in 2021, when I became a semi-independent PI after being awarded a transition grant from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NTU&lt;/a&gt;. And with 2023 comes our fully official start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;old_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;Vintage logo&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;ReBeL logo (2020-2022).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To mark this (re)birth anniversary, we are changing our logo. As much as I loved the old one - which was &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/post/2021-06-30-logo_meaning/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;packed with symbols&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was arguably a bit too&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;extravagant&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Something more sleek and minimal felt good with respect to the lab&amp;rsquo;s newly acquired legitimacy. I know that many will prefer the old-&amp;hellip; sorry, the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vintage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;- logo, and I must say it wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy for me to move forward with the change. Perhaps it will make a come-back in the future in another form, who knows!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new logo contains 3 symbols. The &lt;strong&gt;curved spoon&lt;/strong&gt; is a reference to the Matrix scene where a kid shows Neo how to bend a spoon, which is a &lt;strong&gt;metaphor for reality&lt;/strong&gt; (hence of the name of the lab, reality bending).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Matrix1.gif&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie, Neo becomes able to &lt;strong&gt;control reality by becoming aware of its illusory nature&lt;/strong&gt;, and of the predominant role of one&amp;rsquo;s Self in its generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Matrix2.gif&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&#34;Try to realize the truth... There is no spoon. Then you&#39;ll see that it is not the spoon that bends, it is only yourself.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;second meaning&lt;/strong&gt; of the logo is the &lt;em&gt;Psi&lt;/em&gt; Greek letter, symbol of psychology, formed by the spoon and the white vertical line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;APA.png&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The logo of the APA features the Psi letter.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the black rectangles represent &lt;strong&gt;open doors&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a good illustration of progress, research, discovery and&amp;hellip; consciousness expansion? Interestingly, Jim Morrison named its band &amp;ldquo;The Doors&amp;rdquo; in reference to a quote by William Blake, who said that when &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;the doors of perception were cleansed then everything would appear to man as it is, Infinite&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;TheDoors.jpg&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To share a blooper, here is an alternative direction for the logo that wasn&amp;rsquo;t selected, that incorporated the spoon and the open door in another way. Unfortunately, some said it looked too much like the Pixar lamp, or like a spermatozoid&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;logo_alternative.png&#34; alt=&#34;Alternative logo&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A tentative version of the logo.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
