<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Art | Dr Dominique Makowski</title>
    <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/category/art/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/category/art/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Art</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/media/icon_hu1b87c1310da332ba1b18c001e4f10dac_153312_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Art</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/category/art/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The symbolism behind the ReBeL logo</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-06-30-logo_meaning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-06-30-logo_meaning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Reality Bending logo includes several references to various concepts. &lt;strong&gt;Can you try to guess them?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;👇 👇 👇 👇 👇 👇 👇 👇&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;Spoiler_alert.jpg&#39; width=&#34;90%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- **.**

&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

**.**

&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;

**.**

&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wizard&#34;&gt;Wizard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most striking feature of the logo is the guy in the middle, which represents a wizard. It represent us, the people who delve in the science of &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/post/2020-09-28-what_is_realitybending/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reality bending&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wizards are a powerful &lt;a href=&#34;https://susannabarlow.com/2021/03/26/understanding-the-magician-archetype/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;archetype&lt;/a&gt;, that are primarily defined through the learned ability (by seeking, studying and gathering arcane knowledge) of controlling and manipulating reality. Though many specializations and facets exist, the understanding of the true nature of the world is a core facets that binds all wizards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;gandalf.jpeg&#39; width=&#34;90%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;the wizard Gandalf facing the forces of darkness with his light.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!-- ### Hat --&gt;
&lt;!-- Harry potter? --&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;beard&#34;&gt;Beard&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Greco-Roman antiquity, the beard was seen as the defining feature of a philosopher (see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beard#The_%22Philosopher%27s_beard%22&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Philosopher&amp;rsquo;s beard&lt;/a&gt; on wikipedia), expressing the idea that philosophy is no mere intellectual hobby but rather a way of life that, by definition, transforms every aspect of one&amp;rsquo;s behavior (including one&amp;rsquo;s shaving habits).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Show me your beard and I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you what philosopher you are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cynics had long dirty beards to indicate their &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;strict indifference to all external goods and social customs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stoics were occasionally trimming and washing their beards in accordance with their view &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;that it is acceptable to prefer certain external goods so long as they are never valued above virtue&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Peripatetics took great care of their beards believing in accordance with Aristotle that &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;external goods and social status were necessary for the good life together with virtue&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;beard.jpg&#39; width=&#34;33%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A glorious beard.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;eyepatch&#34;&gt;Eyepatch&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any mythology fan, a bearded figure with an eyepatch (or a missing eye) is known to represent &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Odin&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Odin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the chief deity of the norse pantheon. He&amp;rsquo;s a very complex character, with a deeply ambivalent nature. One of the key moment of Odin&amp;rsquo;s story is when he sacrifices one of his eyes in return for wisdom&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Losing &lt;em&gt;direct sight&lt;/em&gt; of reality in return for a &lt;strong&gt;deeper knowledge&lt;/strong&gt; of reality - here is an interesting idea that we can discuss and (over)interpret with some drinks 🍺&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;odin.jpg&#39; width=&#34;90%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Odin portrayed by one of my favourite actor.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pipe&#34;&gt;Pipe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pipe refers to the most famous painting of the surrealist René Magritte. One of the common interpretation suggests that it symbolizes the difference between the authentic thing (a real pipe) and its representation. This, we believe, is just one level that differentiates the real from the unreal&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;pipe.jpg&#39; width=&#34;90%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Treachery of Images (Magritte, 1929).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;smoke&#34;&gt;Smoke&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smoke takes the form of a Psi letter Ψ, which is the symbol of &lt;strong&gt;psychology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;neuropsydia.png&#39; width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Psi within the brain, a representation of neuropsychology, and the logo of the &lt;a href=&#34;[url](https://github.com/neuropsychology/Neuropsydia.py)&#34;&gt;Neuropsydia&lt;/a&gt; software.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-flower&#34;&gt;The Flower&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;!-- ### The Flower &lt;img src=&#39;Makowski_Poppy.png&#39; title = &#34;The Poppy Flower of the Coat of Arms of the Makowski Family&#34; alt = &#39;The Poppy Flower of the Coat of Arms of the Makowski Family&#39; align=&#34;right&#34; height=&#34;139&#34; /&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flower in the background is not just any flower. It is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poppy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;poppy flower&lt;/a&gt;, from which the seed have been used throughout history to create diverse substances to alter our perception of reality&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, it is also the symbol of the &lt;em&gt;Makowski&lt;/em&gt; family (which names refers to &amp;ldquo;poppy seed&amp;rdquo; in polish).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#39;Makowski_Poppy.png&#39; title = &#34;The Poppy Flower of the Coat of Arms of the Makowski Family&#34; alt = &#39;The Poppy Flower of the Coat of Arms of the Makowski Family&#39; width=&#34;33%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Makowski&#39;s Poppy Flower.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you spot any more 😏? Let us know!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;name-one-thing-in-this-photo&#34;&gt;Name One Thing In This Photo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you name &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; thing in the image above?&lt;/strong&gt; It all looks familiar, but something is off. The image makes &amp;ldquo;sense&amp;rdquo; overall; there are well-defined shapes and objects, that seem to be placed in a plausible - albeit chaotic - fashion, like some random rubbish thrown in the corner of a room. Even the colors, the lightning, the quality, is coherent, and helps making it believable. And yet, chances are you cannot name one single element that composes it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image, after appearing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/melip0ne/status/1120503955526750208?s=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; in April 2019, surfaced on reddit with the caption &amp;ldquo;This picture is &lt;strong&gt;designed to give the viewer the simulated experience of having a stroke&lt;/strong&gt; (particularly in the &lt;strong&gt;occipital lobe&lt;/strong&gt; of the cerebral cortex, where visual perception occurs.) &lt;strong&gt;Everything looks hauntingly familiar but you just can&amp;rsquo;t quite recognize anything&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, and became subsequently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-6959547/Extremely-frustrating-slightly-disturbing-image-goes-viral.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;viral&lt;/a&gt;. However, the author of the caption later admitted that he made this description up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So where does the image come from?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can trace back the original publication to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/0F7XBwFwA-M?t=104&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;instagram account&lt;/a&gt;, which author declared having made the image using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.artbreeder.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ArtBreeder.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This website gives access to an AI algorithm (Generative Adversarial Networks - GAN), commonly used in the processing and generation of images (one mindblowing example can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;thispersondoesnotexist.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which generates realistic pictures of non-existing people). There were even some attempts to &lt;em&gt;reverse engineer&lt;/em&gt; the process to retrieve what the original image could have been like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/original/001/486/325/1dd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, it seems like there is no intelligent design behind this image. No clever neuropsychologist carefully crafting a meaningful experience. Just one of these lucky accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it&amp;rsquo;s still an intriguing image, falling in this uncanny abyss of things that we recognize as familiar, but slightly too alien for our sense-seeking brains to dissolve in meaning. &lt;strong&gt;Could it tell something about brain processes?&lt;/strong&gt; Surely, but &lt;strong&gt;brain disorders?&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;occipital stroke&amp;rdquo; hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt; mentioned above suggests, by its formulation, a lesion to the primary visual cortices. However, as neuroscientists know, these brain regions, located at the extreme back of the brain, are mostly supporting lower level aspects of visual processing, and their damage is usually related to alterations of a somewhat different nature than of that above, such as vision loss, visual hallucinations, visual deformations, loss of color, movement, stereoscopy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is another neuropsychological disorder, referred to as &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;visual agnosia&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, in which patients experience difficulties to recognize visually presented objects, despite preserving an intact vision. In fact, it is more an umbrella term for different subcategories of deficits, and the image above could be reminiscent of visual agnosia of the &lt;em&gt;associative&lt;/em&gt; type, which corresponds to a a specific impairment in the assignment of meaning to a stimulus that is accurately perceived (and can be visually described). This symptom is often related to injuries in the left occipito-temporal region, located on the ventral &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rdquo; stream of the brain (as opposed to the so-called &amp;ldquo;where&amp;rdquo; dorsal stream).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_93a13644dc29f6fc9b30e3c5cd45f521.png 400w,
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_ea5f1132740cb9dd7ec199e8489fa888.png 760w,
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_93a13644dc29f6fc9b30e3c5cd45f521.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;513&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ivan-seals-art&#34;&gt;Ivan Seal&amp;rsquo;s Art&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, the youtuber &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCR6LasBpceuYUhuLToKBzvQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solar Sands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; helped me discover the artist &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Seal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ivan Seal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which work is somewhat akin to the image above. They are not purely abstract renditions, or depictions of impossible entities, but plausible objects that sit in this awkward space, deep between boring reality and total weirdness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://rca-media.rca.ac.uk/images/dumtrimiestonmo_blurosperiod150x100_cm_-_Phot.width-1000.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.redd.it/ywee14vpk8y41.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post_drafts/mandelbrot_monk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post_drafts/mandelbrot_monk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I find &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/python_mandelbrot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fractals fascinating&lt;/a&gt;. Their infinitely self-replicating nature illustrates how complex patterns can emerge from very simple rules. But the history of religions and comparative mythology are other hobbies of mine, and today I have a &lt;strong&gt;little story about fractals, God, or Hell&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;science-and-religions&#34;&gt;Science and Religions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often tend to see religion and science as opposites, one obscurantist and the other enlightening, but such generalization overlooks the vast differences between religions, and thus in the world&amp;rsquo;s understanding of their followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take as example some (mostly extinct) religions, like the polytheisms from antiquity. While the interest in humans of the major Gods was often limited &lt;em&gt;(unless it&amp;rsquo;s about beautiful girls, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeus#Transformation_of_Zeus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zeus&lt;/a&gt; we see you!)&lt;/em&gt;, it was usually considered that regular Men have little say in their destiny, and little power to change it. They were toys in Gods&amp;rsquo; hands, tools at the mercy of their power struggles and agendas not always in line with any form of anthropic benevolence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Fates.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;github for psychologists&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Fates presiding on Human&#39;s destinies, from Disney&#39;s Hercules (1997).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other faiths and philosophies (e.g., Eastern traditions), the world is understood at vastly different scale, and the notion of Self (and/or &amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo;) is extended to encompass many lives. The ultimate goal of breaking the cycle of reincarnation and suffering and ascend to higher states of being is layed out over many lives and, for most people, there isn&amp;rsquo;t much they can do in only one life to escape it. If anything, they must follow a just path, minimize karmic loss, and seek the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; within themselves. A process of Self-mastery and introspection facilitated by various practices, such as meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other religions, refered to as &amp;ldquo;orthopraxic&amp;rdquo;, are more than mere beliefs systems (e.g., Islam, as well as some currents of Judeism) and expect followers to follow a set of behaviours and conducts, codifying many aspects of life. The &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; has already been revealed to mankind, and we have the choice of following it - and be saved - or not - and be damned. Importantly for our topic, the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; is often contained directly in the scriptures, and can only be attained by studying and learning the sacred texts (with varying degrees of possible interpretation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity is different in regards to several aspects.
The history of Chritiniarty led it to regards to several aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corruption
Decadent leaders
Crusades
Inquisition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can get closer to God by studying his creation, the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other religions, personal responsability is even further simplified:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it have to do with fractals? You&amp;rsquo;ll see, but first, let us make a brief reminder on the king of fractals, the Mandelbrot set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://users.math.yale.edu/public_html/People/frame/Fractals/MandelSet/MandelMonk/MandelMonk.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://users.math.yale.edu/public_html/People/frame/Fractals/MandelSet/MandelMonk/MandelMonk.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-mandelbrot&#34;&gt;what is mandelbrot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mandelbrot set exerts some strange attraction, and these blobs of colour
One of the vidualization variant of this set has been immediately attributed a sacred meaning, and has now become known as the Buddhabrot for its eerie ressemblance with the traditional representation of the Buddha in the lotus position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image of Buddhabrot side by side with Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A compilation of the best visual illusions</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-05-13-visual_illusions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-05-13-visual_illusions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-main-source-for-visual-illusions&#34;&gt;The main source for visual illusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Welcome to my illusion website!&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/1DJIwbj0P9&#34;&gt;https://t.co/1DJIwbj0P9&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/SYiK0JvJJl&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/SYiK0JvJJl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Akiyoshi Kitaoka (@AkiyoshiKitaoka) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AkiyoshiKitaoka/status/1253137100582449152?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 23, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;comic&#34;&gt;Comic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;A perceptual illusion walks into the bar... &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/svD1rtRcpT&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/svD1rtRcpT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Jay Van Bavel (@jayvanbavel) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jayvanbavel/status/1295757004124848130?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-deformation&#34;&gt;Illusion of deformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Another amazing illusion from the amazing &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jagarikin?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@jagarikin&lt;/a&gt;: The ring on the left seems to be bigger and expanding, the one on the right smaller and contracting... but they&amp;#39;re both the same size and neither is expanding or contracting at all. 😮 &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/dchwX994PG&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/dchwX994PG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steve Stewart-Williams (@SteveStuWill) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SteveStuWill/status/1295110751309279232?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;August 16, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-rotation&#34;&gt;Illusion of rotation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;ja&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;回転して見えたらRT &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WBoG7rAD2f&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WBoG7rAD2f&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; じゃがりきん (@jagarikin) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jagarikin/status/1286479003910467584?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 24, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-colour&#34;&gt;Illusion of colour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Both people are the same colour in all three panels - an effect called &amp;#39;colour constancy&amp;#39; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/CacNuJo54H&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/CacNuJo54H&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gavin Buckingham (@DrGBuckingham) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DrGBuckingham/status/1279494302968791050?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 4, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-sound-escalation&#34;&gt;Illusion of sound escalation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Something about the continous fall here reminded me of this&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ABeEmdXeNK&#34;&gt;https://t.co/ABeEmdXeNK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amogha Udupa the Chief (@amg_omg) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/amg_omg/status/1278919105341386752?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 3, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-movement-angle&#34;&gt;Illusion of movement angle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The curveball illusion&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The ball is falling straight down, but try not looking directly at it &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/ydJlzfZb0F&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ydJlzfZb0F&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; 〈 Berger | Dillon 〉 (@InertialObservr) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/InertialObservr/status/1278805135850827776?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 2, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-shape&#34;&gt;Illusion of shape&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;When you fixate on the yellow point, do you see dark triangles connecting the discs to the yellow point? Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Pascallisch?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;@Pascallisch&lt;/a&gt;, my old broken movie of the &amp;quot;spokes illusion&amp;quot; has been fixed. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/edvLLXcShO&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/edvLLXcShO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alex Holcombe (@ceptional) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ceptional/status/1278885404142211072?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 3, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-deformation-1&#34;&gt;Illusion of deformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;None of these lines are any more spikey than the others - really powerful illusion by Takahashi (2017) &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/Xr8ncWNNGE&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/Xr8ncWNNGE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gavin Buckingham (@DrGBuckingham) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DrGBuckingham/status/1278385871973122050?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 1, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-colour-1&#34;&gt;Illusion of colour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;In a classic visual illusion, two identical dots look very dissimilar against backgrounds of different colors. A new BCS-led study suggests that this visual processing takes place outside the brain’s visual cortex, possibly within the retina. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/D2NIZJUEye&#34;&gt;https://t.co/D2NIZJUEye&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WrfE4qTmOh&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WrfE4qTmOh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) (@MIT) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/MIT/status/1273270677798297603?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-different-rotation-direction&#34;&gt;Illusion of different rotation direction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;If this does not mess with your visual system, I don&amp;#39;t know what will... &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/vwxATYx39x&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/vwxATYx39x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Tim Kietzmann (@TimKietzmann) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/TimKietzmann/status/1272517256845672450?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 15, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-different-luminance&#34;&gt;Illusion of different luminance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Both pears are the same colour and luminance, despite one seeming brighter than the other &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/KkUJlTI82R&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/KkUJlTI82R&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gavin Buckingham (@DrGBuckingham) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DrGBuckingham/status/1262127098644377601?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-a-light-like-brightness&#34;&gt;Illusion of a &amp;rsquo;light-like&amp;rsquo; brightness&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;And as I have tweeted before, your pupil actually constricts when you look at this illusion, just as it would if you looked at a bright light.  Here&amp;#39;s a paper looking at this phenomenon.  It&amp;#39;s a wonderful illusion.&lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/EAxK4hGLAH&#34;&gt;https://t.co/EAxK4hGLAH&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/aClvekrSN6&#34;&gt;https://t.co/aClvekrSN6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mel_Goodale (@action_brain) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/action_brain/status/1261831522216292352?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;May 17, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-deformation-2&#34;&gt;Illusion of deformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;ja&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;「サクラソウの丘」&lt;br&gt;The checker pattern is aligned vertically and horizontally, but the image appears to bulge out. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/CyCmTPYaDz&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/CyCmTPYaDz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Akiyoshi Kitaoka (@AkiyoshiKitaoka) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AkiyoshiKitaoka/status/1250001227233906689?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 14, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-colour-2&#34;&gt;Illusion of colour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;This is a black and white photograph. Only the lines have colour.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What you “see” is what your 🧠 predicts the reality to be, given the imperfect information it gets. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/gwttlcC2Zw&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/gwttlcC2Zw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Lionel Page (@page_eco) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/page_eco/status/1155077311399489536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 27, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-deformation-3&#34;&gt;Illusion of deformation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Adding small crosses at each intersection makes this perfectly normal grid all wonky! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/DONyCqyh9A&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/DONyCqyh9A&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gavin Buckingham (@DrGBuckingham) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DrGBuckingham/status/1248880110163427330?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 11, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-different-movement-speed&#34;&gt;Illusion of different movement speed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Interesting illusion. The upper rectangle appears to be moving faster. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/LI9Eh7vezy&#34;&gt;https://t.co/LI9Eh7vezy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mel_Goodale (@action_brain) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/action_brain/status/1247373232010862592?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 7, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-different-rotation-direction-1&#34;&gt;Illusion of different rotation direction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Rings appear to rotate clockwise, though they actually rotate counterclockwise.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;(a demo of &amp;quot;reversed phi&amp;quot; produced with phenomenal phenomena) &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/NyfTd12eAl&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/NyfTd12eAl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Akiyoshi Kitaoka (@AkiyoshiKitaoka) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AkiyoshiKitaoka/status/1245547434547109888?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 2, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-movement&#34;&gt;Illusion of movement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Extremely strong effect. One of the best I’ve seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/hCK0URgWrd&#34;&gt;https://t.co/hCK0URgWrd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Thomas Lin Pedersen (@thomasp85) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/thomasp85/status/1228614789473198081?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;February 15, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-different-size&#34;&gt;Illusion of different size&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;I&amp;#39;m biased here, but this is one of the strongest visual illusions I have ever seen.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;None of the colored lines are moving. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/QcW3u6WFB4&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/QcW3u6WFB4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Chris Said (@Chris_Said) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Chris_Said/status/1213217943414136833?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;January 3, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-colour-3&#34;&gt;Illusion of colour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Stare at the centre and see green which is never there! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/kHys53GbUz&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/kHys53GbUz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Gavin Buckingham (@DrGBuckingham) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DrGBuckingham/status/1173212442089984003?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;September 15, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;illusion-of-different-luminance-1&#34;&gt;Illusion of different luminance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;The word &amp;quot;Gray&amp;quot; is always exactly the same shade of gray. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/KYhk3xE0r5&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/KYhk3xE0r5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Robert Volcic (@VolcicR) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/VolcicR/status/1140882128189743105?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;June 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you know other cool visual illusions? Let me know in the comments below!&lt;/strong&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
