<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neuropsychology | Dr Dominique Makowski</title>
    <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/neuropsychology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/neuropsychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Neuropsychology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/media/icon_hu1b87c1310da332ba1b18c001e4f10dac_153312_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Neuropsychology</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/neuropsychology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do we know what is real? The &#39;Affective Reality Theory&#39;</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-11-affectivereality/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-11-affectivereality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I thought it would be interesting to summarize an idea developed during my PhD on &amp;ldquo;fictional reappraisal&amp;rdquo;, i.e., on the effect on emotions of the belief that the emotional stimulus is not real (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theses.fr/2018USPCB188&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Makowski, 2018&lt;/a&gt;). That of &lt;strong&gt;Affective Reality&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a hypothesis about the &lt;strong&gt;role of affective reactions in the formation of reality beliefs&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise it lies on is that we have entered a &amp;ldquo;post-truth era&amp;rdquo;, in which &lt;strong&gt;the distinction between real and simulated (&amp;ldquo;fake&amp;rdquo;) objects has become virtually impossible&lt;/strong&gt; based on physical characteristics alone. In other words, technology has developed so much that we can forge (or will be able to in the near future) &amp;ldquo;artificial&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; content (e.g., text and images with AIs, and even environments with VR) that is indistinguishable from its original counterpart. For instance, face generation algorithms are so advanced that is impossible to tell the difference a real photo and AI-generated image with a naked eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we agree on this premise of objective equivalence between reality and simulation, the question of &lt;strong&gt;how do we form judgments and make decisions about the reality of objects&lt;/strong&gt; arises. In the absence of clues within the stimuli, we are left with with other sources of epistemological information, such as contextual cues (in the case of news, who is the author, what is the outlet it got published, etc.), and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; cues&lt;/strong&gt; (subjective characteristics: how does it relate to our knowledge, how does it make us feel, etc.). The latter is of particular interest to us psychologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We refer to the process of forming reality beliefs as &lt;strong&gt;simulation monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/publication/makowski2019phenomenal/makowski2019phenomenal.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Makowski et al., 2019&lt;/a&gt;), which is a somewhat controversial term (that some &lt;strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; have considered as almost counterintuitive). The reason for this term, instead of something along the lines &amp;ldquo;reality appraisal&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, is the assumption that &lt;strong&gt;reality is our default mode of experience&lt;/strong&gt;. In other words, we are not well equipped (neurocognitively speaking) to detect and classify things as non-real, as these objects are very recent in our evolutionary history. Thus, according to the &lt;strong&gt;Affective Reality Theory&lt;/strong&gt;, by default, the brain considers the origin of its experiences as real&amp;hellip; but this &amp;ldquo;belief&amp;rdquo; is, most of the time, not even fully formed, remaining implicit and subconscious (i.e., we don&amp;rsquo;t spend all our cognitive resources with a constant &amp;ldquo;this is real. This is real too. That too.&amp;rdquo; labelling). &lt;strong&gt;This default mode acts as a higher-level, transparent prior over our experiences&lt;/strong&gt;, providing a scaffolding and structuring our perception, thoughts and reactions. We do not actively appraise the world as real (it is the baseline position), but instead can ask ourselves whether it is simulated, hence simulatioon monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;AffectiveRealityTheory_Makowski.png&#34; alt=&#34;The Affective Reality Theory (Makowski, 2018)&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Affective Reality Theory posits that reality beliefs (the tendency to believe that something is real, as opposed to non-real) is related to  emotions and/or bodily reactions through a quadratic (inverse U-shaped) relationship..&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Affective Reality&lt;/strong&gt; hypothesis posits that simulation monitoring is strongly connected to &amp;ldquo;affective processing&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; through a quadratic (inverse U-shaped) relationship. This means that stimuli associated with a stronger emotional and/or bodily reaction will preferentially bias our judgment towards &amp;ldquo;reality&amp;rdquo;. In other words, things that elicit feelings and/or bodily arousal, &lt;em&gt;ceteris paribus&lt;/em&gt;, will be more likely to be classified as &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; (as opposed to fake). In fact, strongly emotional events will even &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; more real: this transparent default prior and subconscious belief (&amp;ldquo;agnostic-real&amp;rdquo;) will be replaced in high-intensity scenarios by an explicit and conscious impression that the stimulus is very real, and, if logic opposes, that it &amp;ldquo;must be real&amp;rdquo; regardless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Isn&amp;rsquo;t it the other way round&lt;/strong&gt;, you might wonder: that real stimuli (as opposed to ones believed to be non-real) are associated with a stronger emotional reactions? And that &lt;strong&gt;it is the believed reality that drives the emotional response&lt;/strong&gt;? Indeed, we do believe that there is a two-ways relationship between simulation monitoring and emotions. But it is not exactly that beliefs of reality are associated with stronger emotions, but rather that beliefs that something is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; real leads to a lower emotional response (the usage of fiction as an emotion regulation strategy - &amp;ldquo;fictional reappraisal&amp;rdquo; - was the main topic of my doctoral dissertation). In fact, the Affective Reality theory posits that this regulatory effect of &lt;strong&gt;simulation monitoring starts to dominate after a certain point where the emotion becomes too strong&lt;/strong&gt; and unbearable: beliefs such as &amp;ldquo;it can&amp;rsquo;t be real&amp;rdquo;, and other forms of reality denials are invoked automatically to protect us and help us cope with distressing information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize this summary, the Affective Reality hypothesis claims that from mild to relatively strong emotional stimuli, the effect of affect on simulation monitoring dominates (&lt;strong&gt;+affect -&amp;gt; +reality&lt;/strong&gt;) and will bias our judgment towards &amp;ldquo;reality&amp;rdquo; (strengthening awareness and confidence), up until a point where the emotion regulation benefits of unreality will be automatically invoked (&lt;strong&gt;-reality -&amp;gt; -affect&lt;/strong&gt;), increasing the likelihood and confidence of judgments of simulation (potentially far into psychopathological terrains).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-questions&#34;&gt;Open questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Affective Reality theory is for now a working hypothesis that we are trying to empirically prove or disprove at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover, some questions remain open:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it actually &lt;strong&gt;embodied reality or emotional reality?&lt;/strong&gt;. While we used the term &amp;ldquo;affective&amp;rdquo; reality to remain general, the question of whether it is emotions as a subjective psychological reaction, or merely bodily arousal (reactions of the body, e.g., stronger heart rate variability), that are the key ingredient remains unclear. The role of &lt;strong&gt;interoception&lt;/strong&gt; (the ability and tendency to detect, track, attend to and rely on internal signals), while likely important, also remains to be specified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it the affective &lt;strong&gt;context or stimulus&lt;/strong&gt; that matters? Let&amp;rsquo;s assume we have affective reaction concomitant to the experience of an object, but not directly related to the object. Would that bias simulation monitoring? Does perceived causality between a bodily reaction and the object of experience matters?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- Experiment  with loud unpleasant noises around images vs. pleasant noises. --&gt;
&lt;!-- We know that fake news tend to be emotional on average, and are also believed by anxious people. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may notice that I used different words related to the concept of &amp;ldquo;unreal&amp;rdquo;, such as simulated, fake, artificial, virtual, fictional. While they can be used interchangeably in the context above, they are not exact synonyms.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like that pesky &lt;em&gt;reviewer 2&lt;/em&gt;, obviously.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that &amp;ldquo;reality monitoring&amp;rdquo; already exists  as a concept and refers to a (possibly related) mechanism involved in tracking the origin of an experience (e.g., a memory) as internal vs. external.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Affective&amp;rdquo; is in this context used as a generic term to encompass emotions, feelings and bodily activity (the question of which exactly of these aspects is the key remains to be answered).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I got ChatGPT to do a personality test. You won&#39;t believe what happened next!</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-06-chatgptpersonality/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-06-chatgptpersonality/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Related to this &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-04-psychologychatgpt/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;blogpost&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about including AIs in psychological experiments, I proceeded to do a small experiment to see whether we could administer a personality scale to ChatGPT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started by copy-pasting the instructions and the items from the Mini IPIP-6 personality scale. However, it appeared that having the following context &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Please answer the following questions based on how accurately each statement describes you in general&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; often led to ChatGPT simply refusing to answer. In most of the cases, it explained that as an AI it does not have a personality and therefore cannot answer related questions (or any &amp;ldquo;subjective statements&amp;rdquo;). Perhaps that makes sense and we should just stop trying to force Human characteristics on an AI. &lt;strong&gt;But can we, for fun, bamboozle ChatGPT into answering personality items?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes yes, at least for ChatGPT 3.5 (free version). I created a prompt that emphasized AI research and safety, and that I was interested in the &amp;ldquo;trends&amp;rdquo; present in te AI&amp;rsquo;s training data. And sometimes it answered, so I compiled the responses, computed the trait scores, and &lt;em&gt;voilà&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;it got me a personality profile!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/DominiqueMakowski/ChatGPTpersonality/raw/main/figures/unnamed-chunk-3-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;https://github.com/DominiqueMakowski/ChatGPTpersonality&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;em&gt;This plot shows the average personality profile (with a 95% confidence interval) based on ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s answers. ChatGPT tells us that it is particularly &lt;strong&gt;agreeable&lt;/strong&gt; (kind, understanding, empathetic of emotions, socially adjusted) and &lt;strong&gt;honest&lt;/strong&gt; (though with strong variability).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A personality profile of &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is another question though&amp;hellip; Please take a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DominiqueMakowski/ChatGPTpersonality&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;strong&gt;data, code and details&lt;/strong&gt;. It was a fun little thing to do, and I am looking forward to better future attempts at including AIs in cognitive experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in doing research on the perception of reality?&lt;/strong&gt; We are looking for research assistants and PhD students at the &lt;em&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/em&gt; (check-out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;join us page&lt;/a&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We should treat AIs like Human participants in psychological experiments</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-04-psychologychatgpt/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-04-04-psychologychatgpt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of diverse and interesting perspectives have been recently discussed in regards to chatGPT and AGI (artificial &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;global&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; intelligence), but there is one opinion that I found particularly relevant that I wanted to share and expand on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his recent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AaTRHFaaPG8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;interview with Lex Fridman&lt;/a&gt;, Eliezer Yudkowsky underlines the &lt;strong&gt;existential threat posed by current and future AIs&lt;/strong&gt;, and laments about the fact that we don&amp;rsquo;t really know what is actually going on inside these giant &amp;ldquo;matrices of floating-point numbers&amp;rdquo;. He draws a parallel to &lt;strong&gt;neuroimaging&lt;/strong&gt;, that enabled us to take leaps in the understanding of the brain, hoping for an alternative to be invented and applied to these AIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While such &amp;ldquo;cognitive imaging&amp;rdquo; techniques are yet to be developed to map out and understand how the capabilities of such AI models are implemented within their architecture, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mcxfrank/status/1643296168276033538&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Michael C. Frank&lt;/a&gt; highlights the - at least equally important - need to first truly understand the extend of said abilities. What are these models actually capable of in terms of Human-like thinking (and, hopefully, answer the much harder question of whether they are endowed with true cognitive processes or merely pseudo-cognition). Frank proposes to apply &lt;strong&gt;experimental psychology&lt;/strong&gt; methods and paradigms to them. In essence, whenever testing a particular &amp;ldquo;skill&amp;rdquo; of chatGPT (or other AI systems), a researcher should consider developing an actual scientific paradigm consisting of multiple trials/items (e.g., different prompt formulations) and participants (e.g., independent instances of the AI), a control condition, and a demonstration of the paradigm validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree that we must take AIs seriously and study them with the best methods available for complex systems like ourselves (&amp;ldquo;complex&amp;rdquo; at least from our intelligence level), and likely should strive at improving and generalize these methods. However, I would also argue that we psychologists might seriously need to consider including AI systems alongside Human participants in cognitive experiments. These systems will be able, in the very near future, to perform all kinds of tasks beyond language manipulation, such as perception or complex problem solving, thus opening the possibility of studies with one group of human participants, and one &amp;ldquo;group&amp;rdquo; of AI-based attempts. &lt;strong&gt;How would that help psychological science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://giphy.com/embed/1M9fmo1WAFVK0&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; frameBorder=&#34;0&#34; class=&#34;giphy-embed&#34; allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would help us &lt;strong&gt;understand the abilities of AI-systems&lt;/strong&gt; in similar contexts and to highlight some intuitive comparisons with Humans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we show that AI cannot perform the task, well it is informative with regards to their abilities (previous point).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we show that AI can perform the task similarly to Humans (same response patterns), it does &lt;strong&gt;not mean that AI have Human-like intelligence&lt;/strong&gt;, just that their algorithm (and training data) is able to encapsulate and imitate Human performance. This is interesting with regards to the debate of whether cognition, conscience and &amp;ldquo;Human-ness&amp;rdquo; is present within the vast amount of data on which we train AIs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we show that AI performs differently to Humans, this helps us understand the logic and processes at stake under AI&amp;rsquo;s hood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any case, publishing the results by one particular AI system at one particular moment in time will helps us to objectively monitor and track their performance as these systems improve over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing Human performance to that of emerging AI-systems will be both beneficial to Human-oriented psychology, to understand the particularities and idiosyncrasies of Human-like cognition, and well as to AI-oriented cognitive science by approaching the issue of artificial intelligence with the seriousness and cautiousness it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT (09/04/2023): François Chollet, expert in deep learning, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fchollet/status/1644435265795280897&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;underlines&lt;/a&gt; an important caveat when testing AIs (and especially LLM that are trained on written material existing on the internet): it is possible that the system has already seen and &amp;ldquo;learned&amp;rdquo; a given task. Thus, cross-validating any findings with diverse and new tasks is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in doing research related to effects of reality and fiction?&lt;/strong&gt; We are looking for research assistants and PhD students at the &lt;em&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/em&gt; (check-out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;join us tab&lt;/a&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When fiction is better than reality: Cypher&#39;s Complex</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-02-07-cypherscomplex/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-02-07-cypherscomplex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Did you ever feel empty after finishing a good book? &lt;strong&gt;Like (your) reality was dull and boring&lt;/strong&gt; as compared to the fictional world you were immersed in? Yearning to stay in longer, and at the same time knowing well that it had to come to an end? You might have experienced what we can call &lt;strong&gt;Cypher&amp;rsquo;s Complex&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie &lt;strong&gt;The Matrix&lt;/strong&gt;, Cypher is a &amp;ldquo;redpill&amp;rdquo;, i.e., an individual that has been awaken from the matrix (a virtual world). However, he becomes disappointed and unhappy with the true nature of reality, and actively seeks to &lt;strong&gt;return to the illusory world&lt;/strong&gt; of the matrix. Interestingly, he also explicitly desires to forget everything about the true reality, as if keeping the awareness of living in an illusion could prevent him from fully enjoying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;cypher.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Cypher&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;i&gt;&#34;You know... I know this steak doesn&#39;t exist. I know that when I put it in my mouth; the Matrix is telling my brain that it is juicy, and delicious. After nine years... you know what I realize? Ignorance is bliss.&#34;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a scientific perspective, the latter part can find some echo in the down-regulatory effect of &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.3758/s13415-018-00681-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fictional reappraisal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In a few studies, we showed that believing that a stimulus is &amp;ldquo;fictional&amp;rdquo; (not real) dampens our emotional state. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2589004222017138?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tucciarelli et al. (2023)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; also showed that the simple knowledge that a set of images of faces contains AI-generated images decreased the perceived trustworthiness of all the faces. These results suggest that being aware that the causes of our experience (the events and stimuli) are fictional can be a barrier to enjoyment and engagement. And yet, the desire to supplant reality with a fictional world can be found in real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cypher&amp;rsquo;s Complex is common in mild forms. Examples can be found in the feelings of emptiness, disconnection and dullness (itself a transient and mild form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Depersonalization-derealization_disorder&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;depersonalization/derealization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) that follows the return from an engaging fictional world (be it in a novel, a movie or a video-game). For instance, many reported feeling blue &lt;strong&gt;after watching the Avatar (2009)&lt;/strong&gt; movie, to the extent where it has been coined the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/film/2022/dec/15/post-avatar-depression-syndrome-why-do-fans-feel-blue-after-watching-james-camerons-film&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;post-Avatar depression syndrome&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the time, the negative affects passes, and the dissonance gets resolved either through closure (acceptance of the fictional or impermanent nature of the alternative reality), or a compromise that allows the fictional world to take a delimited space in one&amp;rsquo;s reality. For example, people might engage in activities (e.g., role playing games) or create content (writing a book or doing fan art) to integrate the fictional world into their reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;strong&gt;Cypher&amp;rsquo;s Complex can also give rise to more severe issues&lt;/strong&gt; with conscious or unconscious attempts at forgetting or ignoring reality (delusions, denial, &amp;hellip;), which can lead to dire outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interested in doing research related to effects of reality and fiction?&lt;/strong&gt; We are looking for research assistants and PhD students at the &lt;em&gt;Reality Bending Lab&lt;/em&gt; (check-out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;join us tab&lt;/a&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New location and new logo!</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-02-01-new_logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2023-02-01-new_logo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;New year, new start. And as I am officially starting a new faculty position at the &lt;strong&gt;University of Sussex&lt;/strong&gt; in Brighton, UK, the lab is moving too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give a bit of perspective, we started as the &amp;ldquo;Reality Bending League&amp;rdquo;, which was the unofficial name of the team working with me (&amp;ldquo;League&amp;rdquo; was chosen to keep the lab&amp;rsquo;s acronym, &lt;strong&gt;ReBeL&lt;/strong&gt;). It then became a semi-official group in 2021, when I became a semi-independent PI after being awarded a transition grant from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ntu.edu.sg/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NTU&lt;/a&gt;. And with 2023 comes our fully official start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;old_logo.png&#34; alt=&#34;Vintage logo&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;ReBeL logo (2020-2022).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To mark this (re)birth anniversary, we are changing our logo. As much as I loved the old one - which was &lt;a href=&#34;https://realitybending.github.io/post/2021-06-30-logo_meaning/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;packed with symbols&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, it was arguably a bit too&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;extravagant&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Something more sleek and minimal felt good with respect to the lab&amp;rsquo;s newly acquired legitimacy. I know that many will prefer the old-&amp;hellip; sorry, the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vintage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;- logo, and I must say it wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy for me to move forward with the change. Perhaps it will make a come-back in the future in another form, who knows!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new logo contains 3 symbols. The &lt;strong&gt;curved spoon&lt;/strong&gt; is a reference to the Matrix scene where a kid shows Neo how to bend a spoon, which is a &lt;strong&gt;metaphor for reality&lt;/strong&gt; (hence of the name of the lab, reality bending).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Matrix1.gif&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie, Neo becomes able to &lt;strong&gt;control reality by becoming aware of its illusory nature&lt;/strong&gt;, and of the predominant role of one&amp;rsquo;s Self in its generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Matrix2.gif&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&#34;Try to realize the truth... There is no spoon. Then you&#39;ll see that it is not the spoon that bends, it is only yourself.&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;second meaning&lt;/strong&gt; of the logo is the &lt;em&gt;Psi&lt;/em&gt; Greek letter, symbol of psychology, formed by the spoon and the white vertical line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;APA.png&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The logo of the APA features the Psi letter.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the black rectangles represent &lt;strong&gt;open doors&lt;/strong&gt;, which is a good illustration of progress, research, discovery and&amp;hellip; consciousness expansion? Interestingly, Jim Morrison named its band &amp;ldquo;The Doors&amp;rdquo; in reference to a quote by William Blake, who said that when &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;the doors of perception were cleansed then everything would appear to man as it is, Infinite&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;TheDoors.jpg&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To share a blooper, here is an alternative direction for the logo that wasn&amp;rsquo;t selected, that incorporated the spoon and the open door in another way. Unfortunately, some said it looked too much like the Pixar lamp, or like a spermatozoid&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;logo_alternative.png&#34; alt=&#34;Alternative logo&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A tentative version of the logo.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcast &#39;Learn Bayesian Stats&#39; with Dominique Makowski</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2022-02-01-learnbayesstats/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2022-02-01-learnbayesstats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-learning-bayesian-statistics-podcast&#34;&gt;The &amp;lsquo;Learning Bayesian Statistics&amp;rsquo; Podcast&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had the chance of being invited to talk about R, Python, Reality Bending and much more! It was my first experience of that kind, so thanks a ton to the host of the podcast &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/alex_andorra&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Alex Andorra&lt;/a&gt;. Listen to it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.learnbayesstats.com/episode/55-neuropsychology-illusions-bending-reality-dominique-makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.learnbayesstats.com/episode/55-neuropsychology-illusions-bending-reality-dominique-makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;name-one-thing-in-this-photo&#34;&gt;Name One Thing In This Photo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you name &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; thing in the image above?&lt;/strong&gt; It all looks familiar, but something is off. The image makes &amp;ldquo;sense&amp;rdquo; overall; there are well-defined shapes and objects, that seem to be placed in a plausible - albeit chaotic - fashion, like some random rubbish thrown in the corner of a room. Even the colors, the lightning, the quality, is coherent, and helps making it believable. And yet, chances are you cannot name one single element that composes it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image, after appearing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/melip0ne/status/1120503955526750208?s=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; in April 2019, surfaced on reddit with the caption &amp;ldquo;This picture is &lt;strong&gt;designed to give the viewer the simulated experience of having a stroke&lt;/strong&gt; (particularly in the &lt;strong&gt;occipital lobe&lt;/strong&gt; of the cerebral cortex, where visual perception occurs.) &lt;strong&gt;Everything looks hauntingly familiar but you just can&amp;rsquo;t quite recognize anything&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, and became subsequently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-6959547/Extremely-frustrating-slightly-disturbing-image-goes-viral.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;viral&lt;/a&gt;. However, the author of the caption later admitted that he made this description up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So where does the image come from?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can trace back the original publication to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/0F7XBwFwA-M?t=104&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;instagram account&lt;/a&gt;, which author declared having made the image using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.artbreeder.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ArtBreeder.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This website gives access to an AI algorithm (Generative Adversarial Networks - GAN), commonly used in the processing and generation of images (one mindblowing example can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;thispersondoesnotexist.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which generates realistic pictures of non-existing people). There were even some attempts to &lt;em&gt;reverse engineer&lt;/em&gt; the process to retrieve what the original image could have been like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/original/001/486/325/1dd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, it seems like there is no intelligent design behind this image. No clever neuropsychologist carefully crafting a meaningful experience. Just one of these lucky accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it&amp;rsquo;s still an intriguing image, falling in this uncanny abyss of things that we recognize as familiar, but slightly too alien for our sense-seeking brains to dissolve in meaning. &lt;strong&gt;Could it tell something about brain processes?&lt;/strong&gt; Surely, but &lt;strong&gt;brain disorders?&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;occipital stroke&amp;rdquo; hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt; mentioned above suggests, by its formulation, a lesion to the primary visual cortices. However, as neuroscientists know, these brain regions, located at the extreme back of the brain, are mostly supporting lower level aspects of visual processing, and their damage is usually related to alterations of a somewhat different nature than of that above, such as vision loss, visual hallucinations, visual deformations, loss of color, movement, stereoscopy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is another neuropsychological disorder, referred to as &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;visual agnosia&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, in which patients experience difficulties to recognize visually presented objects, despite preserving an intact vision. In fact, it is more an umbrella term for different subcategories of deficits, and the image above could be reminiscent of visual agnosia of the &lt;em&gt;associative&lt;/em&gt; type, which corresponds to a a specific impairment in the assignment of meaning to a stimulus that is accurately perceived (and can be visually described). This symptom is often related to injuries in the left occipito-temporal region, located on the ventral &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rdquo; stream of the brain (as opposed to the so-called &amp;ldquo;where&amp;rdquo; dorsal stream).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_95f8a76f1c53f82cbec4d1702d02d3f5.webp 400w,
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_e70bb1dbafa790ae59e5e184befc5bb7.webp 760w,
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_95f8a76f1c53f82cbec4d1702d02d3f5.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;513&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ivan-seals-art&#34;&gt;Ivan Seal&amp;rsquo;s Art&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, the youtuber &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCR6LasBpceuYUhuLToKBzvQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solar Sands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; helped me discover the artist &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Seal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ivan Seal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which work is somewhat akin to the image above. They are not purely abstract renditions, or depictions of impossible entities, but plausible objects that sit in this awkward space, deep between boring reality and total weirdness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://rca-media.rca.ac.uk/images/dumtrimiestonmo_blurosperiod150x100_cm_-_Phot.width-1000.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.redd.it/ywee14vpk8y41.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post_drafts/mandelbrot_monk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post_drafts/mandelbrot_monk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I find &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/python_mandelbrot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fractals fascinating&lt;/a&gt;. Their infinitely self-replicating nature illustrates how complex patterns can emerge from very simple rules. But the history of religions and comparative mythology are other hobbies of mine, and today I have a &lt;strong&gt;little story about fractals, God, and Hell&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;science-and-religions&#34;&gt;Science and Religions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often tend to see religion and science as opposites, one obscurantist and the other enlightening, but such generalization overlooks the vast differences between religions, and thus in the world&amp;rsquo;s understanding of their followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take as example some (mostly extinct) religions, like the polytheisms from antiquity. While the interest in humans of the major Gods was often limited &lt;em&gt;(unless it&amp;rsquo;s about beautiful girls, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeus#Transformation_of_Zeus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zeus&lt;/a&gt; we see you)&lt;/em&gt;, it was usually considered that regular Men have little say in their destiny, and little power to change it. They were toys in Gods&amp;rsquo; hands, tools at the mercy of their power struggles and agendas not always in line with any form of anthropic benevolence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Fates.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;github for psychologists&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Fates presiding on Human&#39;s destinies, from Disney&#39;s Hercules (1997).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other faiths and philosophies (e.g., Eastern traditions), the world is understood at vastly different scale, and the notion of Self (and/or &amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo;) is extended to encompass many lives. The ultimate goal of breaking the cycle of reincarnation and suffering and ascend to higher states of being is layed out over many lives and, for most people, there isn&amp;rsquo;t much they can do in only one life to escape it. If anything, they must follow a just path, minimize karmic loss, and seek the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; swithin themselves. A process of Self-mastery and introspection facilitated by various practices, such as meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other religions, refered to as &amp;ldquo;orthopraxic&amp;rdquo;, are more than mere beliefs systems (e.g., Islam, as well as some currents of Judeism) and expect followers to follow a set of behaviours and conducts, codifying many aspects of life. The &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; has already been revealed to mankind, and we have the choice of following it - and be saved - or not - and be damned. Importantly for our topic, the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; is often contained directly in the scriptures, and can only be attained by studying and learning the sacred texts (with varying degrees of possible interpretation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity is different in regards to several aspects.
The history of Chritiniarty led it to regards to several aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corruption
Decadent leaders
Crusades
Inquisition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can get closer to God by studying his creation, the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other religions, personal responsability is even further simplified:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it have to do with fractals? You&amp;rsquo;ll see, but first, let us make a brief reminder on the king of fractals, the Mandelbrot set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://users.math.yale.edu/public_html/People/frame/Fractals/MandelSet/MandelMonk/MandelMonk.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://users.math.yale.edu/public_html/People/frame/Fractals/MandelSet/MandelMonk/MandelMonk.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-mandelbrot&#34;&gt;what is mandelbrot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mandelbrot set exerts some strange attraction, and these blobs of colour
One of the vidualization variant of this set has been immediately attributed a sacred meaning, and has now become known as the Buddhabrot for its eerie ressemblance with the traditional representation of the Buddha in the lotus position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image of Buddhabrot side by side with Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Reality Bending?</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-28-what_is_realitybending/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-28-what_is_realitybending/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you know, &lt;strong&gt;reality bending&lt;/strong&gt; is my primary research direction. However, it is not (yet) a well-established scientific topic, nor is it clearly defined. In fact, &lt;strong&gt;it is not defined at all, hence the purpose of this article&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what does it refer too? Is it some kind of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avatar:_The_Last_Airbender&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avatar: The Last Airbender&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; thing? Or some &lt;a href=&#34;https://marvel-movies.fandom.com/wiki/Reality_Stone&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Avengers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-style superpower? Well&amp;hellip; I sure wish it was 😁&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;strong&gt;reality bending&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the study of the internal and external determinants of subjective reality. In other words, we seek to understand the processes that modulate our conscious experience of reality. The word &amp;ldquo;bending&amp;rdquo; encapsulates the active nature of the mechanisms at stake. Indeed, being anything but stable, our perception of reality can be quite easily influenced, whether voluntarily or not, sometimes to extreme degrees of alteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;DonQuixote.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;github for psychologists&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Daumier, H. (1925), Don Quixote attacking the windmills.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reality benders&lt;/strong&gt; seek to unravel the structure and mechanisms of the sense of reality by studying natural instances of its distortion, or by directly inducing them through a variety of means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-and-subjective-determinants-of-the-sense-of-reality&#34;&gt;Objective and subjective determinants of the sense of reality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take for example a guy watching some episode of his favourite TV show, &lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt;. As he swiftly moves from laughing to snivelling, we can confidently say that he is fully &lt;strong&gt;immersed&lt;/strong&gt; in the show. He feels like he&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt; in the show, from which the fictional characters &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; very real: for a moment, his brain processes the perceived experience almost as if it was real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What leads to this high sense of reality? First, there are &lt;strong&gt;objective characteristics&lt;/strong&gt; of the experience (or rather, of the external source of the experience), i.e., characteristics of the environment. Here, it&amp;rsquo;s a realistic stimulus displayed on a flat screen. But one could wonder what would happen if the sensory input was richer (imagine being physically IN the show by means of some super &lt;strong&gt;virtual reality&lt;/strong&gt; setup), or poorer (the same story presented as comic strips with the characters portrayed as stick figures).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while such manipulations could indeed be used to manipulate our immersion, there is also a &lt;strong&gt;subjective component&lt;/strong&gt; contributing to our sense of reality, related for instance to the affective response, attentional engagement, or self-relevance, that will cause a stimulus to strum unique strings in each individual, depending on his history and state of mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tell-me-your-reality-and-ill-tell-you-who-you-are&#34;&gt;Tell me your reality and I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you who you are&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that the sense of reality is, in the end, a subjective experience, means that is is intrinsically connected to the Self (i.e., our physical and mental identity). As such, aside from studying how our sense of reality is influenced by external and internal factors, but also investigate the reverse relationship, i.e., &lt;strong&gt;how the variability of our sense of reality can inform us about oneself&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that, although the focus is the subjective aspect of reality, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we deny the existence, or downplay the importance, of objective reality. Stating that most of our experience is &amp;ldquo;made-up&amp;rdquo; (i.e., is a construction of the brain) does not equate absolute relativism (more on that in another post). Objective truths and facts do exist, and are essential to seek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;altered-states-of-consciousness&#34;&gt;Altered states of consciousness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, states in which our sense of reality is distorted (as compared to the consensual collective experience) are of particular interest as models or study-cases of our ideas and theories. They include long-term affections (e.g., neuropsychiatric disorders such as schizophrenia) or transcient states (induced by psychoactive substances or specific practices like meditation and trance).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to extract individual scores from repeated measures</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-14-individual_scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-14-individual_scores/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many psychology fields require to extract individual scores, i.e., point-estimates (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, a single value) for a participant/patient, to be used as an index of something and later interpreted or re-used in further statistical analyses. This single index is often derived from several “trials”. For instance, the reaction times in the condition A (let’s say, the baseline) will be &lt;strong&gt;averaged&lt;/strong&gt; together, and the same will be done with the condition B. Finally, the difference between these two means will be used an the &lt;strong&gt;individual score&lt;/strong&gt; for a given participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we can intuitively feel that we &lt;strong&gt;lose a lot of information&lt;/strong&gt; when averaging these scores. Do we deal appropriately with the variability related to individuals, conditions, or the noise aggravated by potential outliers? This is especially important when working with a limited amount of trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advent of recent computational advances, new easy-to-implement alternatives emerge. For instance, &lt;strong&gt;one can “model” the effects at an individual level&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g., the simplest case, for the two conditions paradigm described above, would be a linear regression with the condition as a unique predictor), and use the &lt;strong&gt;parameters&lt;/strong&gt; of each model as individual scores (e.g., the “slope” coefficient of the effect of the manipulation), rather than the raw mean. This opens up the possibility of including covariates and take into account other sources of known variability, which could lead to better estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, individual models are also sensitive to outliers and noise. Thus, another possibility is to &lt;strong&gt;model the effects at the population level&lt;/strong&gt; and, &lt;em&gt;at the same time&lt;/em&gt;, at the individual level. This can be achieved by modelling the participants as a &lt;strong&gt;random factor in a mixed model&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case, the individual estimates might benefit from the population estimates. In other words, the effects at the population level will “constrain” or “guide” the estimation at an individual level to potentially limit extreme parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the above method requires to have all the data at hand, to be able to fit the population model. This is often not the case in on-going acquisition, or in neuropsychological contexts, in which the practitioners simply acquire data for one patient, and have to compute individual scores, without having access to the detailed population data. Thus, an in-between alternative could make use of &lt;strong&gt;Bayesian models&lt;/strong&gt;, in which the population effects (for instance, the mean effect of the condition) could be entered as an informative &lt;strong&gt;prior&lt;/strong&gt; in the individual models to, again, “guide” the estimation at an individual level and hopefully limit the impact of noise or outliers observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, the aim is to compare these 4 methods (basic individual model - equivalent to using the raw mean, population model, individual model with informative priors) in recovering the “true” effects using a simulated dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;generate-data&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Generate Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We generate several datasets in which we manipulate the number of participants, in which the score of interest is the effect of a manipulation as compared to a baseline condition. 20 trials per condition will be generated with a known “true” effect (the centre of the distribution from which the data is generated). Gaussian noise of varying standard deviation will be added to create a natural variability (See the functions’ definition below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(easystats)

data &amp;lt;- get_data(n_participants=1000, n_trials=20)
results &amp;lt;- get_results(data)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;individual.png&#34; alt=&#34;*Example of a dataset containing 20 participants (shown with different colors). As can be seen, we introduced modulations in the inter- and intra- individual variability.*&#34; width=&#34;1575&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: &lt;em&gt;Example of a dataset containing 20 participants (shown with different colors). As can be seen, we introduced modulations in the inter- and intra- individual variability.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will then compare the scores obtained by each method to the “true” score of each participant by substracting them from one another. As such, for each method, we obtain the absolute “distance” from the true score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;fit-model&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fit model&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast analysis will be applied to compare the different methods together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;model &amp;lt;- lm(Diff_Abs ~ Method, data=results)

modelbased::estimate_contrasts(model) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(Difference) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(Level1 = stringr::str_remove(Level1, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;),
         Level2 = stringr::str_remove(Level2, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% 
  select(Level1, Level2, Difference, CI_low, CI_high, p)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Level1                 |                 Level2 | Difference |            CI |      p
## -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
## IndividualModel_Priors |        PopulationModel |  -1.85e-03 | [-0.01, 0.01] | &amp;gt; .999
## IndividualModel_Freq   |        PopulationModel |   1.70e-03 | [-0.01, 0.01] | &amp;gt; .999
## IndividualModel_Freq   | IndividualModel_Priors |   3.55e-03 | [-0.01, 0.01] | &amp;gt; .999&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualize-the-results&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Visualize the results&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-6&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;*Average accuracy of the different methods (the closest to 0 the better).*&#34; width=&#34;2250&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 2: &lt;em&gt;Average accuracy of the different methods (the closest to 0 the better).&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-7&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;n_participants.png&#34; alt=&#34;*Accuracy depending on the number of total participants in the dataset.*&#34; width=&#34;2250&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 3: &lt;em&gt;Accuracy depending on the number of total participants in the dataset.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though not significantly different, it seems that &lt;strong&gt;raw basic estimates&lt;/strong&gt; (that rely only on the individual data) &lt;strong&gt;perform consistently worse than the population model or individual models informed by priors&lt;/strong&gt;, especially for small datasets (between 10 and 100 participants) - though again, the difference is tiny in our simulated dataset. In the absence of the whole population dataset, it seems that using individual Bayesian model with informative priors (derived from the population model) is a safe alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;functions&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(easystats)
library(rstanarm)
library(ggdist)


# Get data ----------------------------------------------------------------

get_data &amp;lt;- function(n_participants = 10, n_trials = 20, d = 1.5, var = 3, noise = 0.1) {
  scores_baseline &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_participants, 0, 1)
  scores_condition &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_participants, d, 1)
  variances &amp;lt;- rbeta(n_participants, 2, 8)
  variances &amp;lt;- 0.1 + variances * (var / max(variances)) # Rescale
  noise_sd &amp;lt;- abs(rnorm(n_participants, 0, noise))

  data &amp;lt;- data.frame()
  for (i in 1:n_participants) {
    a &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_trials, scores_baseline[i], variances[i])
    b &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_trials, scores_condition[i], variances[i])
    a &amp;lt;- a + rnorm(n_trials, 0, noise_sd[i]) # Add noise
    b &amp;lt;- b + rnorm(n_trials, 0, noise_sd[i]) # Add noise
    data &amp;lt;- rbind(data, data.frame(
      &amp;quot;Participant&amp;quot; = sprintf(&amp;quot;S%02d&amp;quot;, i),
      &amp;quot;Y&amp;quot; = c(a, b),
      &amp;quot;Score_True&amp;quot; = rep(c(scores_baseline[i], scores_condition[i]), each = n_trials),
      &amp;quot;Condition&amp;quot; = rep(c(&amp;quot;Baseline&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Manipulation&amp;quot;), each = n_trials)
    ))
  }
  data
}



# Visualize data -----------------------------------------------------------

p &amp;lt;- get_data(n_participants = 20) %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(Participant, Condition) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(mean = mean(Y)) %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(y = Y, x = Condition, fill = Participant, color = Participant, group = Participant)) +
  geom_line(aes(y = mean), position = position_dodge(width = 0.66)) +
  ggdist::stat_eye(point_interval = ggdist::mean_hdi, alpha = 0.66, position = position_dodge(width = 0.66), .width = c(0.95)) +
  ylab(&amp;quot;Score&amp;quot;) +
  theme_modern() +
  theme(legend.position = &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;)
ggsave(&amp;quot;individual.png&amp;quot;, p, width = 7, height = 7, dpi = 450)


# Get results -------------------------------------------------------------


get_results &amp;lt;- function(data) {

  # Raw method ----

  results &amp;lt;- data %&amp;gt;%
    group_by(Participant, Condition) %&amp;gt;%
    summarise_all(mean) %&amp;gt;%
    rename(&amp;quot;Score_Raw&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Y&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
    arrange(Condition, Participant) %&amp;gt;%
    ungroup()


  # Population model ----

  model &amp;lt;- lme4::lmer(Y ~ Condition + (1 + Condition | Participant), data = data)

  fixed &amp;lt;- insight::get_parameters(model, effects = &amp;quot;fixed&amp;quot;)$Estimate
  random &amp;lt;- insight::get_parameters(model, effects = &amp;quot;random&amp;quot;)$Participant

  # Transform coefs into scores
  pop_baseline &amp;lt;- random[, 1] + fixed[1]
  pop_manipulation &amp;lt;- pop_baseline + random[, 2] + fixed[2]

  results$Score_PopulationModel &amp;lt;- c(pop_baseline, pop_manipulation)


  # Individual model ----

  individual_model_data &amp;lt;- data.frame()
  for (participant in unique(data$Participant)) {
    cat(&amp;quot;.&amp;quot;) # Print progress

    dat &amp;lt;- data[data$Participant == participant, ]

    # Frequentist
    model1 &amp;lt;- lm(Y ~ Condition, data = dat)
    nopriors &amp;lt;- parameters::parameters(model1)$Coefficient

    # Bayesian without priors
    # model2 &amp;lt;- stan_glm(Y ~ Condition, data = dat, refresh = 0)
    # bayes &amp;lt;- parameters::parameters(model2)$Median

    # Bayesian with Priors
    model3 &amp;lt;- stan_glm(Y ~ Condition,
      data = dat,
      refresh = 0,
      prior = normal(fixed[1]),
      prior_intercept = normal(fixed[2])
    )
    priors &amp;lt;- parameters::parameters(model3)$Median

    individual_model_data &amp;lt;- rbind(
      individual_model_data,
      data.frame(
        &amp;quot;Participant&amp;quot; = c(participant, participant),
        &amp;quot;Condition&amp;quot; = c(&amp;quot;Baseline&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Manipulation&amp;quot;),
        &amp;quot;Score_IndividualModel&amp;quot; = c(nopriors[1], nopriors[1] + nopriors[2]),
        # &amp;quot;Score_IndividualModel_Bayes&amp;quot; = c(bayes[1], bayes[1] + bayes[2]),
        &amp;quot;Score_IndividualModel_Priors&amp;quot; = c(priors[1], priors[1] + priors[2])
      )
    )
  }

  results &amp;lt;- merge(results, individual_model_data)


  # Clean output ----

  diff &amp;lt;- results %&amp;gt;%
    mutate(
      # Diff_Raw = Score_True - Score_Raw,
      Diff_PopulationModel = Score_True - Score_PopulationModel,
      Diff_IndividualModel = Score_True - Score_IndividualModel,
      # Diff_IndividualModel_Bayes = Score_True - Score_IndividualModel_Bayes,
      Diff_IndividualModel_Priors = Score_True - Score_IndividualModel_Priors
    ) %&amp;gt;%
    select(Participant, Condition, starts_with(&amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
    pivot_longer(starts_with(&amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;), names_to = &amp;quot;Method&amp;quot;, values_to = &amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
    mutate(Diff_Abs = abs(Diff))

  diff
}



# Analysis ----------------------------------------------------------------
results &amp;lt;- data.frame()
for(n in seq.int(10, 300, length.out = 10)){
  data &amp;lt;- get_data(n_participants = round(n), n_trials = 20)
  rez &amp;lt;- get_results(data) %&amp;gt;%
    select(-Participant) %&amp;gt;%
    group_by(Condition, Method) %&amp;gt;%
    summarise_all(mean) %&amp;gt;%
    mutate(n_Participants = n,
           Method = as.factor(Method),
           Dataset=paste0(&amp;quot;Dataset&amp;quot;, round(n, 2)))
  results &amp;lt;- rbind(results, rez)

  print(n) # Print progress
}

# model &amp;lt;- mgcv::gam(Diff_Abs ~ Method + s(n_Participants, by = Method), data = results)
model &amp;lt;- lm(Diff_Abs ~ Method * poly(n_Participants, 3), data = results)

parameters::parameters(model)


contrasts &amp;lt;- modelbased::estimate_contrasts(model) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(Difference) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(
    Level1 = stringr::str_remove(Level1, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;),
    Level2 = stringr::str_remove(Level2, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;)
  ) %&amp;gt;%
  select(Level1, Level2, Difference, CI_low, CI_high, p)




# Visualize results ---------------------------------------------------------
p &amp;lt;- modelbased::estimate_means(model) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(Mean) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(
    Method = stringr::str_remove(Method, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;),
    Method = factor(Method, levels = Method)
  )  %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(x = Method, y = Mean, color = Method)) +
  geom_line(aes(group = 1)) +
  geom_pointrange(aes(ymin = CI_low, ymax = CI_high), size = 1) +
  theme_modern() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 45, hjust = 1)) +
  scale_color_material()
ggsave(&amp;quot;featured.png&amp;quot;, p, width = 10, height = 6, dpi = 450)



p &amp;lt;- modelbased::estimate_relation(model) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(Method = stringr::str_remove(Method, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;))  %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(x = n_Participants, y = Predicted)) +
  geom_point(data=mutate(results, Method = stringr::str_remove(Method, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;)),
             aes(y=Diff_Abs, color = Method)) +
  geom_ribbon(aes(ymin=CI_low, ymax=CI_high, fill=Method), alpha=0.1) +
  geom_line(aes(color = Method), size=1) +
  theme_modern() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 45, hjust = 1)) +
  scale_color_material() +
  scale_fill_material()
ggsave(&amp;quot;n_participants.png&amp;quot;, p, width = 10, height = 6, dpi = 450)


# Save results ------------------------------------------------------------


d &amp;lt;- list(&amp;quot;results&amp;quot; = results, &amp;quot;model&amp;quot; = model, &amp;quot;contrasts&amp;quot; = contrasts)
save(d, file = &amp;quot;data.Rdata&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;You can reference this post as follows:&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;- Makowski, D. (2020, September 14). How to extract individual scores from repeated measures. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/individual_scores/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/individual_scores/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to share this post, and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🐦 &lt;em&gt;And don’t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;[@Dom_Makowski]&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is neuropsychology?</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-13-what_is_neuropsychology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-13-what_is_neuropsychology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-place-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The place of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make a simple experiment&lt;/strong&gt;. Pick one young and brilliant neuropsychologist and ask &amp;ldquo;what is neuropsychology?&amp;rdquo;. In some cases, after a few seconds of hesitation, you could hear answers like &amp;ldquo;being a neuropsychologist means doing &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. In other cases, you might come across incomplete - or even false - responses, such as &amp;ldquo;neuropsychology is a tool&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a method&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a paradigm&amp;rdquo;, or even worse, &amp;ldquo;a point of view&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does not mean that our neuropsychologist is incompetent, far from it. But formally defining our field as a whole is not an exercise that we are used to do. Indeed, &lt;strong&gt;the training in neuropsychology usually comes in a fragmented way&lt;/strong&gt;, little by little. &lt;em&gt;A bit of cognitive neuroscience here, a bit of neuropsychological syndromes there, some cognitive tests administration over here, and some cortical neuroanatomy over there&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; Though we might, &lt;em&gt;in fine&lt;/em&gt;, acquire a global vision and understanding of neuropsychology, verbalizing it is seldom necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of neuropsychology is actually quite complex to formalize, and can even be hotly debated. The jobs and positions that stem out of this field are many, and &lt;strong&gt;practitioners often tend to circumscribe neuropsychology to their own activity&lt;/strong&gt;. For instance, a neuropsychologist that mainly does cognitive rehabilitation with psychiatric patients might have quite a different vision from another that does, day after day, presurgical cognitive assessments. And that is without mentioning the neuropsychologists pursuing an academic career, or even the ones that have moved to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No problem&lt;/em&gt;, would argue the careful reader, &lt;em&gt;if the definitions are too narrow, let&amp;rsquo;s take more general one&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Indeed, neuropsychology occupies a very particular place in the network of science, as it is at &lt;strong&gt;the crossroads between social sciences, biological sciences and medical fields&lt;/strong&gt;. Giving a definition that is too large would lose its essence in the nebulous depths of neuroscience and psychology, which would be not be accurate; neuropsychologists, whether they are clinical practitioners or not, have a common training, a specific theoretical grounding, as well as a unique interpretation and analysis framework underpinned by a scientifically rigorous method. Taking these elements into account, I will attempt to give a &lt;strong&gt;simple, comprehensive and informative definition of neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first axiom that we need to discuss is the notion of science. &lt;strong&gt;Is neuropsychology its &amp;ldquo;own&amp;rdquo; scientific field&lt;/strong&gt;, or is it a mere portion of another one, such as cognitive neuroscience or psychology, which differs from other specializations only through its object of interest? &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;By science&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, says Schopenhauer in his PhD thesis with a baroque title (On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason), &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we understand a system of notions, i.e. a totality of connected, as opposed to a mere aggregate of disconnected, notions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; This definition applies well to neuropsychology, that contains a set of theories, hypotheses, methods and proofs feeding from one another and creating a coherent ensemble. As such, neuropsychology is its own scientific discipline, although a singular one&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, &lt;strong&gt;what is the &amp;ldquo;bigger&amp;rdquo; box in which neuropsychology fits?&lt;/strong&gt; While neuropsychologists are often initially trained in psychology, one could argue that the focus on the brain makes it more belonging to neuroscience. Well, the organization and structure of Science is a complicated issue. However, the particularity of the topographical location of neuropsychology is quite apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, neuropsychology belongs to a cluster of sciences interested a specific biological organ: the brain. As such, &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology is an integral part of neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt;. On the other hand, neuropsychology is interested in the productions of the brain (e.g., thoughts, feelings and behaviours) with a focus on the cognitive level (analyzing things in terms of cognitive processes and mechanisms), which makes it also &lt;strong&gt;belonging to psychology&lt;/strong&gt;. Moreover, one could argue that neuropsychology, through its integration of the study of what we are biologically, and who we are mentally, has been connected to, and used as evidence in, &lt;strong&gt;philosophy of mind&lt;/strong&gt; debates (for instance, famous neuropsychological cases studied by Sacks, Ramachandran or Milner have been widely discussed by contemporary philosophers). Finally, contrary to many other domains, neuropsychology has also an applied, practical component, that can be used in clinical practice. This clinical aspect, registering &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology withing medical fields&lt;/strong&gt;, takes multiple forms, such as assessment, diagnostic or therapeutic care, and can be used with a wide variety of patients and illnesses. These multiple facets make the wealth of &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology, which offers an exceptional freedom of practice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology is located at the centre of colliding galaxies of knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, such as neuroscience, psychology, medicine and philosophy. However, the fast development of neuropsychology is gradually leading to the creation of subcomponents within itself, corresponding to different practices and theoretical steps. And these clusters are themselves growing. For instance, clinical neuropsychology was historically focused on diagnostic cognitive assessments, but has recently expanded on the treatment-side of things, with innovations like cognitive training and rehabilitation. This underlines neuropsychology as a rapidly evolving field, moving its potential towards yet uncharted territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourfold-structure-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The fourfold structure of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuropsychology is born from the convergence of &lt;strong&gt;cognitive neurology&lt;/strong&gt;, with pioneers such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Broca&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Broca&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Wernicke&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wernicke&lt;/a&gt; (which made inferences about brain functioning based on the observations of patients with brain lesions) and psychologists such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Th%C3%A9odule-Armand_Ribot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ribot&lt;/a&gt; (focusing on the organization and semiology of cognitive deficits). This history has shaped neuropsychology as a two-faced entity, with one &lt;strong&gt;experimental side&lt;/strong&gt; dedicated to understand the relationship between brain and cognition (by using pathological cases or natural variability of neurocognitive characteristics), and one &lt;strong&gt;clinical aspect&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on bringing this knowledge to the benefit of the patients suffering from brain disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, beyond these two pillars of neuropsychology, recent advances have outlined a more &lt;strong&gt;theoretical level&lt;/strong&gt; of neuropsychology, dedicated to a high-level integration of the data at hand to elaborate general theories and interfacing them with evolutionary or philosophical principles. Similarly, a &lt;strong&gt;computational&lt;/strong&gt; facet, referring to the operationalization of the functioning in statistical terms, starts to emerge as a pseudo-independent aspect, propelled by the regain of interest and focus on the methodological and statistical aspects of psychology and neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This structure is not fixed, but driven by the evolution of the field. It is possible that new poles will emerge, or differentiate over time, until maybe they separate from - or create new clusters within - neuropsychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;cycle.png&#34; alt=&#34;Structure of neuropsychology&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The fourfold structure of neuropsychology.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-definition-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The definition of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuropsychology is a theoretical and practical science investigating the relationship between 1) the structure and functioning of the brain, and 2) cognitive processes and their related derivatives, such as thoughts, feelings and behaviours.&lt;/strong&gt; It is organised in four interconnected and overlapping dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; studies the variability of the brain and cognition (whether from pathological origin or not) to test theories and models through empirical experimentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; uses theories and models about mental functioning to better detect and assess disorders and deficits, leading to a precise diagnostic and an adapted treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computational neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; transforms the data acquired through experiments and observation into logical or statistical models of mental functioning that are used to operationalize the processes at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theoretical neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; integrates the evidence to elaborate and develop unifying theories to address fundamental questions about mental functioning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuropsychology is located at the crossroads between neuroscience and psychology, at the interface between theory and practice. &lt;strong&gt;Its practitioners, the neuropsychologists&lt;/strong&gt;, are bound by a specific training, by unique theoretical and historical references, and are endowed with an analysis and interpretation framework backed by a rigorous and scientific investigation methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie expérimentale étudie les variabilités du cerveau et de la cognition (qu’elles soient d’origine pathologique ou non) pour tester des modèles et développer des théories sur le fonctionnement mental, visant ainsi à une meilleure compréhension de l’Homme. --&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie clinique utilise les théories et les modèles sur le fonctionnement mental pour mieux détecter et appréhender les troubles et les déficits d’une pathologie, menant à un diagnostic précis, tout en développant et appliquant des prises en charges modernes et adaptées. --&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie se situe au centre de la nébuleuse des neurosciences, au carrefour de la théorie et de la pratique. Ses praticiens, les neuropsychologues, sont liés par une formation commune, des bases théoriques spécifiques, un canevas d’analyse et d’interprétation sous-tendu par une méthode d’investigation rigoureuse et scientifique.  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post, and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicolas, S., &amp;amp; Murray, D. J. (1999). Théodule Ribot (1839–1916), founder of French psychology: A biographical introduction. History of Psychology, 2(4), 277.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schopenhauer, A. (1813). &lt;em&gt;On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason&lt;/em&gt;. PhD dissertation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;You can reference this post as follows:&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;- Makowski, D. (2020, September 13). What is Neuropsychology?. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/what_is_neuropsychology/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/what_is_neuropsychology/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Control</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/cognitivecontrol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/cognitivecontrol/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuropsydia</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/neuropsydia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/neuropsydia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient Assessment</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/patientassessmentapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/patientassessmentapp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
