<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neuropsychology | Dr Dominique Makowski</title>
    <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/neuropsychology/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/neuropsychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Neuropsychology</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/media/icon_hud75d04f2b1977d0bc7efdcf2aeb84fcd_760423_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Neuropsychology</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/tag/neuropsychology/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;name-one-thing-in-this-photo&#34;&gt;Name One Thing In This Photo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you name &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; thing in the image above?&lt;/strong&gt; It all looks familiar, but something is off. The image makes &amp;ldquo;sense&amp;rdquo; overall; there are well-defined shapes and objects, that seem to be placed in a plausible - albeit chaotic - fashion, like some random rubbish thrown in the corner of a room. Even the colors, the lightning, the quality, is coherent, and helps making it believable. And yet, chances are you cannot name one single element that composes it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image, after appearing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/melip0ne/status/1120503955526750208?s=20&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; in April 2019, surfaced on reddit with the caption &amp;ldquo;This picture is &lt;strong&gt;designed to give the viewer the simulated experience of having a stroke&lt;/strong&gt; (particularly in the &lt;strong&gt;occipital lobe&lt;/strong&gt; of the cerebral cortex, where visual perception occurs.) &lt;strong&gt;Everything looks hauntingly familiar but you just can&amp;rsquo;t quite recognize anything&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, and became subsequently &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-6959547/Extremely-frustrating-slightly-disturbing-image-goes-viral.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;viral&lt;/a&gt;. However, the author of the caption later admitted that he made this description up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;So where does the image come from?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can trace back the original publication to an &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/0F7XBwFwA-M?t=104&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;instagram account&lt;/a&gt;, which author declared having made the image using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.artbreeder.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ArtBreeder.com&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This website gives access to an AI algorithm (Generative Adversarial Networks - GAN), commonly used in the processing and generation of images (one mindblowing example can be found on &lt;a href=&#34;https://thispersondoesnotexist.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;thispersondoesnotexist.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which generates realistic pictures of non-existing people). There were even some attempts to &lt;em&gt;reverse engineer&lt;/em&gt; the process to retrieve what the original image could have been like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.kym-cdn.com/photos/images/original/001/486/325/1dd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all, it seems like there is no intelligent design behind this image. No clever neuropsychologist carefully crafting a meaningful experience. Just one of these lucky accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, it&amp;rsquo;s still an intriguing image, falling in this uncanny abyss of things that we recognize as familiar, but slightly too alien for our sense-seeking brains to dissolve in meaning. &lt;strong&gt;Could it tell something about brain processes?&lt;/strong&gt; Surely, but &lt;strong&gt;brain disorders?&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;occipital stroke&amp;rdquo; hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt; mentioned above suggests, by its formulation, a lesion to the primary visual cortices. However, as neuroscientists know, these brain regions, located at the extreme back of the brain, are mostly supporting lower level aspects of visual processing, and their damage is usually related to alterations of a somewhat different nature than of that above, such as vision loss, visual hallucinations, visual deformations, loss of color, movement, stereoscopy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is another neuropsychological disorder, referred to as &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;visual agnosia&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;, in which patients experience difficulties to recognize visually presented objects, despite preserving an intact vision. In fact, it is more an umbrella term for different subcategories of deficits, and the image above could be reminiscent of visual agnosia of the &lt;em&gt;associative&lt;/em&gt; type, which corresponds to a a specific impairment in the assignment of meaning to a stimulus that is accurately perceived (and can be visually described). This symptom is often related to injuries in the left occipito-temporal region, located on the ventral &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rdquo; stream of the brain (as opposed to the so-called &amp;ldquo;where&amp;rdquo; dorsal stream).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_93a13644dc29f6fc9b30e3c5cd45f521.png 400w,
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_ea5f1132740cb9dd7ec199e8489fa888.png 760w,
               /post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_1200x1200_fit_lanczos_3.png 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2021-01-03-visual_agnosia/whatstream_hu7b3e2a15287cf91a80e194bf11a946d3_304646_93a13644dc29f6fc9b30e3c5cd45f521.png&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;513&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ivan-seals-art&#34;&gt;Ivan Seal&amp;rsquo;s Art&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, the youtuber &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCR6LasBpceuYUhuLToKBzvQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solar Sands&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; helped me discover the artist &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ivan_Seal&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ivan Seal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which work is somewhat akin to the image above. They are not purely abstract renditions, or depictions of impossible entities, but plausible objects that sit in this awkward space, deep between boring reality and total weirdness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://rca-media.rca.ac.uk/images/dumtrimiestonmo_blurosperiod150x100_cm_-_Phot.width-1000.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://i.redd.it/ywee14vpk8y41.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What visual agnosia might feel like</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post_drafts/mandelbrot_monk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post_drafts/mandelbrot_monk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I find &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/python_mandelbrot/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;fractals fascinating&lt;/a&gt;. Their infinitely self-replicating nature illustrates how complex patterns can emerge from very simple rules. But the history of religions and comparative mythology are other hobbies of mine, and today I have a &lt;strong&gt;little story about fractals, God, or Hell&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;science-and-religions&#34;&gt;Science and Religions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often tend to see religion and science as opposites, one obscurantist and the other enlightening, but such generalization overlooks the vast differences between religions, and thus in the world&amp;rsquo;s understanding of their followers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take as example some (mostly extinct) religions, like the polytheisms from antiquity. While the interest in humans of the major Gods was often limited &lt;em&gt;(unless it&amp;rsquo;s about beautiful girls, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeus#Transformation_of_Zeus&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zeus&lt;/a&gt; we see you!)&lt;/em&gt;, it was usually considered that regular Men have little say in their destiny, and little power to change it. They were toys in Gods&#39; hands, tools at the mercy of their power struggles and agendas not always in line with any form of anthropic benevolence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;Fates.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;github for psychologists&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Fates presiding on Human&#39;s destinies, from Disney&#39;s Hercules (1997).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other faiths and philosophies (e.g., Eastern traditions), the world is understood at vastly different scale, and the notion of Self (and/or &amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo;) is extended to encompass many lives. The ultimate goal of breaking the cycle of reincarnation and suffering and ascend to higher states of being is layed out over many lives and, for most people, there isn&amp;rsquo;t much they can do in only one life to escape it. If anything, they must follow a just path, minimize karmic loss, and seek the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; within themselves. A process of Self-mastery and introspection facilitated by various practices, such as meditation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other religions, refered to as &amp;ldquo;orthopraxic&amp;rdquo;, are more than mere beliefs systems (e.g., Islam, as well as some currents of Judeism) and expect followers to follow a set of behaviours and conducts, codifying many aspects of life. The &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; has already been revealed to mankind, and we have the choice of following it - and be saved - or not - and be damned. Importantly for our topic, the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; is often contained directly in the scriptures, and can only be attained by studying and learning the sacred texts (with varying degrees of possible interpretation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity is different in regards to several aspects.
The history of Chritiniarty led it to regards to several aspects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corruption
Decadent leaders
Crusades
Inquisition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can get closer to God by studying his creation, the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other religions, personal responsability is even further simplified:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it have to do with fractals? You&amp;rsquo;ll see, but first, let us make a brief reminder on the king of fractals, the Mandelbrot set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://users.math.yale.edu/public_html/People/frame/Fractals/MandelSet/MandelMonk/MandelMonk.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://users.math.yale.edu/public_html/People/frame/Fractals/MandelSet/MandelMonk/MandelMonk.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-mandelbrot&#34;&gt;what is mandelbrot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mandelbrot set exerts some strange attraction, and these blobs of colour
One of the vidualization variant of this set has been immediately attributed a sacred meaning, and has now become known as the Buddhabrot for its eerie ressemblance with the traditional representation of the Buddha in the lotus position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image of Buddhabrot side by side with Buddha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post and don&amp;rsquo;t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; 🐦 &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;@Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to extract individual scores from repeated measures</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-14-individual_scores/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-14-individual_scores/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many psychology fields require to extract individual scores, i.e., point-estimates (&lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;, a single value) for a participant/patient, to be used as an index of something and later interpreted or re-used in further statistical analyses. This single index is often derived from several “trials”. For instance, the reaction times in the condition A (let’s say, the baseline) will be &lt;strong&gt;averaged&lt;/strong&gt; together, and the same will be done with the condition B. Finally, the difference between these two means will be used an the &lt;strong&gt;individual score&lt;/strong&gt; for a given participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we can intuitively feel that we &lt;strong&gt;lose a lot of information&lt;/strong&gt; when averaging these scores. Do we deal appropriately with the variability related to individuals, conditions, or the noise aggravated by potential outliers? This is especially important when working with a limited amount of trials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the advent of recent computational advances, new easy-to-implement alternatives emerge. For instance, &lt;strong&gt;one can “model” the effects at an individual level&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g., the simplest case, for the two conditions paradigm described above, would be a linear regression with the condition as a unique predictor), and use the &lt;strong&gt;parameters&lt;/strong&gt; of each model as individual scores (e.g., the “slope” coefficient of the effect of the manipulation), rather than the raw mean. This opens up the possibility of including covariates and take into account other sources of known variability, which could lead to better estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, individual models are also sensitive to outliers and noise. Thus, another possibility is to &lt;strong&gt;model the effects at the population level&lt;/strong&gt; and, &lt;em&gt;at the same time&lt;/em&gt;, at the individual level. This can be achieved by modelling the participants as a &lt;strong&gt;random factor in a mixed model&lt;/strong&gt;. In this case, the individual estimates might benefit from the population estimates. In other words, the effects at the population level will “constrain” or “guide” the estimation at an individual level to potentially limit extreme parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the above method requires to have all the data at hand, to be able to fit the population model. This is often not the case in on-going acquisition, or in neuropsychological contexts, in which the practitioners simply acquire data for one patient, and have to compute individual scores, without having access to the detailed population data. Thus, an in-between alternative could make use of &lt;strong&gt;Bayesian models&lt;/strong&gt;, in which the population effects (for instance, the mean effect of the condition) could be entered as an informative &lt;strong&gt;prior&lt;/strong&gt; in the individual models to, again, “guide” the estimation at an individual level and hopefully limit the impact of noise or outliers observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, the aim is to compare these 4 methods (basic individual model - equivalent to using the raw mean, population model, individual model with informative priors) in recovering the “true” effects using a simulated dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;generate-data&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Generate Data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We generate several datasets in which we manipulate the number of participants, in which the score of interest is the effect of a manipulation as compared to a baseline condition. 20 trials per condition will be generated with a known “true” effect (the centre of the distribution from which the data is generated). Gaussian noise of varying standard deviation will be added to create a natural variability (See the functions’ definition below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(easystats)

data &amp;lt;- get_data(n_participants=1000, n_trials=20)
results &amp;lt;- get_results(data)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-3&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;individual.png&#34; alt=&#34;*Example of a dataset containing 20 participants (shown with different colors). As can be seen, we introduced modulations in the inter- and intra- individual variability.*&#34; width=&#34;1575&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: &lt;em&gt;Example of a dataset containing 20 participants (shown with different colors). As can be seen, we introduced modulations in the inter- and intra- individual variability.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will then compare the scores obtained by each method to the “true” score of each participant by substracting them from one another. As such, for each method, we obtain the absolute “distance” from the true score.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;fit-model&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Fit model&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrast analysis will be applied to compare the different methods together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;model &amp;lt;- lm(Diff_Abs ~ Method, data=results)

modelbased::estimate_contrasts(model) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(Difference) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(Level1 = stringr::str_remove(Level1, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;),
         Level2 = stringr::str_remove(Level2, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;% 
  select(Level1, Level2, Difference, CI_low, CI_high, p)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;## Level1                 |                 Level2 | Difference |            CI |      p
## -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
## IndividualModel_Priors |        PopulationModel |  -1.85e-03 | [-0.01, 0.01] | &amp;gt; .999
## IndividualModel_Freq   |        PopulationModel |   1.70e-03 | [-0.01, 0.01] | &amp;gt; .999
## IndividualModel_Freq   | IndividualModel_Priors |   3.55e-03 | [-0.01, 0.01] | &amp;gt; .999&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;visualize-the-results&#34; class=&#34;section level4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Visualize the results&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-6&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;featured.png&#34; alt=&#34;*Average accuracy of the different methods (the closest to 0 the better).*&#34; width=&#34;2250&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 2: &lt;em&gt;Average accuracy of the different methods (the closest to 0 the better).&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:unnamed-chunk-7&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;n_participants.png&#34; alt=&#34;*Accuracy depending on the number of total participants in the dataset.*&#34; width=&#34;2250&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 3: &lt;em&gt;Accuracy depending on the number of total participants in the dataset.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusion&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though not significantly different, it seems that &lt;strong&gt;raw basic estimates&lt;/strong&gt; (that rely only on the individual data) &lt;strong&gt;perform consistently worse than the population model or individual models informed by priors&lt;/strong&gt;, especially for small datasets (between 10 and 100 participants) - though again, the difference is tiny in our simulated dataset. In the absence of the whole population dataset, it seems that using individual Bayesian model with informative priors (derived from the population model) is a safe alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;functions&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Functions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(easystats)
library(rstanarm)
library(ggdist)


# Get data ----------------------------------------------------------------

get_data &amp;lt;- function(n_participants = 10, n_trials = 20, d = 1.5, var = 3, noise = 0.1) {
  scores_baseline &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_participants, 0, 1)
  scores_condition &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_participants, d, 1)
  variances &amp;lt;- rbeta(n_participants, 2, 8)
  variances &amp;lt;- 0.1 + variances * (var / max(variances)) # Rescale
  noise_sd &amp;lt;- abs(rnorm(n_participants, 0, noise))

  data &amp;lt;- data.frame()
  for (i in 1:n_participants) {
    a &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_trials, scores_baseline[i], variances[i])
    b &amp;lt;- rnorm(n_trials, scores_condition[i], variances[i])
    a &amp;lt;- a + rnorm(n_trials, 0, noise_sd[i]) # Add noise
    b &amp;lt;- b + rnorm(n_trials, 0, noise_sd[i]) # Add noise
    data &amp;lt;- rbind(data, data.frame(
      &amp;quot;Participant&amp;quot; = sprintf(&amp;quot;S%02d&amp;quot;, i),
      &amp;quot;Y&amp;quot; = c(a, b),
      &amp;quot;Score_True&amp;quot; = rep(c(scores_baseline[i], scores_condition[i]), each = n_trials),
      &amp;quot;Condition&amp;quot; = rep(c(&amp;quot;Baseline&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Manipulation&amp;quot;), each = n_trials)
    ))
  }
  data
}



# Visualize data -----------------------------------------------------------

p &amp;lt;- get_data(n_participants = 20) %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(Participant, Condition) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(mean = mean(Y)) %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(y = Y, x = Condition, fill = Participant, color = Participant, group = Participant)) +
  geom_line(aes(y = mean), position = position_dodge(width = 0.66)) +
  ggdist::stat_eye(point_interval = ggdist::mean_hdi, alpha = 0.66, position = position_dodge(width = 0.66), .width = c(0.95)) +
  ylab(&amp;quot;Score&amp;quot;) +
  theme_modern() +
  theme(legend.position = &amp;quot;none&amp;quot;)
ggsave(&amp;quot;individual.png&amp;quot;, p, width = 7, height = 7, dpi = 450)


# Get results -------------------------------------------------------------


get_results &amp;lt;- function(data) {

  # Raw method ----

  results &amp;lt;- data %&amp;gt;%
    group_by(Participant, Condition) %&amp;gt;%
    summarise_all(mean) %&amp;gt;%
    rename(&amp;quot;Score_Raw&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;Y&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
    arrange(Condition, Participant) %&amp;gt;%
    ungroup()


  # Population model ----

  model &amp;lt;- lme4::lmer(Y ~ Condition + (1 + Condition | Participant), data = data)

  fixed &amp;lt;- insight::get_parameters(model, effects = &amp;quot;fixed&amp;quot;)$Estimate
  random &amp;lt;- insight::get_parameters(model, effects = &amp;quot;random&amp;quot;)$Participant

  # Transform coefs into scores
  pop_baseline &amp;lt;- random[, 1] + fixed[1]
  pop_manipulation &amp;lt;- pop_baseline + random[, 2] + fixed[2]

  results$Score_PopulationModel &amp;lt;- c(pop_baseline, pop_manipulation)


  # Individual model ----

  individual_model_data &amp;lt;- data.frame()
  for (participant in unique(data$Participant)) {
    cat(&amp;quot;.&amp;quot;) # Print progress

    dat &amp;lt;- data[data$Participant == participant, ]

    # Frequentist
    model1 &amp;lt;- lm(Y ~ Condition, data = dat)
    nopriors &amp;lt;- parameters::parameters(model1)$Coefficient

    # Bayesian without priors
    # model2 &amp;lt;- stan_glm(Y ~ Condition, data = dat, refresh = 0)
    # bayes &amp;lt;- parameters::parameters(model2)$Median

    # Bayesian with Priors
    model3 &amp;lt;- stan_glm(Y ~ Condition,
      data = dat,
      refresh = 0,
      prior = normal(fixed[1]),
      prior_intercept = normal(fixed[2])
    )
    priors &amp;lt;- parameters::parameters(model3)$Median

    individual_model_data &amp;lt;- rbind(
      individual_model_data,
      data.frame(
        &amp;quot;Participant&amp;quot; = c(participant, participant),
        &amp;quot;Condition&amp;quot; = c(&amp;quot;Baseline&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Manipulation&amp;quot;),
        &amp;quot;Score_IndividualModel&amp;quot; = c(nopriors[1], nopriors[1] + nopriors[2]),
        # &amp;quot;Score_IndividualModel_Bayes&amp;quot; = c(bayes[1], bayes[1] + bayes[2]),
        &amp;quot;Score_IndividualModel_Priors&amp;quot; = c(priors[1], priors[1] + priors[2])
      )
    )
  }

  results &amp;lt;- merge(results, individual_model_data)


  # Clean output ----

  diff &amp;lt;- results %&amp;gt;%
    mutate(
      # Diff_Raw = Score_True - Score_Raw,
      Diff_PopulationModel = Score_True - Score_PopulationModel,
      Diff_IndividualModel = Score_True - Score_IndividualModel,
      # Diff_IndividualModel_Bayes = Score_True - Score_IndividualModel_Bayes,
      Diff_IndividualModel_Priors = Score_True - Score_IndividualModel_Priors
    ) %&amp;gt;%
    select(Participant, Condition, starts_with(&amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
    pivot_longer(starts_with(&amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;), names_to = &amp;quot;Method&amp;quot;, values_to = &amp;quot;Diff&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
    mutate(Diff_Abs = abs(Diff))

  diff
}



# Analysis ----------------------------------------------------------------
results &amp;lt;- data.frame()
for(n in seq.int(10, 300, length.out = 10)){
  data &amp;lt;- get_data(n_participants = round(n), n_trials = 20)
  rez &amp;lt;- get_results(data) %&amp;gt;%
    select(-Participant) %&amp;gt;%
    group_by(Condition, Method) %&amp;gt;%
    summarise_all(mean) %&amp;gt;%
    mutate(n_Participants = n,
           Method = as.factor(Method),
           Dataset=paste0(&amp;quot;Dataset&amp;quot;, round(n, 2)))
  results &amp;lt;- rbind(results, rez)

  print(n) # Print progress
}

# model &amp;lt;- mgcv::gam(Diff_Abs ~ Method + s(n_Participants, by = Method), data = results)
model &amp;lt;- lm(Diff_Abs ~ Method * poly(n_Participants, 3), data = results)

parameters::parameters(model)


contrasts &amp;lt;- modelbased::estimate_contrasts(model) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(Difference) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(
    Level1 = stringr::str_remove(Level1, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;),
    Level2 = stringr::str_remove(Level2, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;)
  ) %&amp;gt;%
  select(Level1, Level2, Difference, CI_low, CI_high, p)




# Visualize results ---------------------------------------------------------
p &amp;lt;- modelbased::estimate_means(model) %&amp;gt;%
  arrange(Mean) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(
    Method = stringr::str_remove(Method, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;),
    Method = factor(Method, levels = Method)
  )  %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(x = Method, y = Mean, color = Method)) +
  geom_line(aes(group = 1)) +
  geom_pointrange(aes(ymin = CI_low, ymax = CI_high), size = 1) +
  theme_modern() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 45, hjust = 1)) +
  scale_color_material()
ggsave(&amp;quot;featured.png&amp;quot;, p, width = 10, height = 6, dpi = 450)



p &amp;lt;- modelbased::estimate_relation(model) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(Method = stringr::str_remove(Method, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;))  %&amp;gt;%
  ggplot(aes(x = n_Participants, y = Predicted)) +
  geom_point(data=mutate(results, Method = stringr::str_remove(Method, &amp;quot;Diff_&amp;quot;)),
             aes(y=Diff_Abs, color = Method)) +
  geom_ribbon(aes(ymin=CI_low, ymax=CI_high, fill=Method), alpha=0.1) +
  geom_line(aes(color = Method), size=1) +
  theme_modern() +
  theme(axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 45, hjust = 1)) +
  scale_color_material() +
  scale_fill_material()
ggsave(&amp;quot;n_participants.png&amp;quot;, p, width = 10, height = 6, dpi = 450)


# Save results ------------------------------------------------------------


d &amp;lt;- list(&amp;quot;results&amp;quot; = results, &amp;quot;model&amp;quot; = model, &amp;quot;contrasts&amp;quot; = contrasts)
save(d, file = &amp;quot;data.Rdata&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;references&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;You can reference this post as follows:&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;- Makowski, D. (2020, September 14). How to extract individual scores from repeated measures. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/individual_scores/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/individual_scores/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to share this post, and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🐦 &lt;em&gt;And don’t forget to join me on Twitter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;[@Dom_Makowski]&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://twitter.com/Dom_Makowski&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is neuropsychology?</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-13-what_is_neuropsychology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/2020-09-13-what_is_neuropsychology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-place-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The place of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s make a simple experiment&lt;/strong&gt;. Pick one young and brilliant neuropsychologist and ask &amp;ldquo;what is neuropsychology?&amp;rdquo;. In some cases, after a few seconds of hesitation, you could hear answers like &amp;ldquo;being a neuropsychologist means doing &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. In other cases, you might come across incomplete - or even false - responses, such as &amp;ldquo;neuropsychology is a tool&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a method&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a paradigm&amp;rdquo;, or even worse, &amp;ldquo;a point of view&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does not mean that our neuropsychologist is incompetent, far from it. But formally defining our field as a whole is not an exercise that we are used to do. Indeed, &lt;strong&gt;the training in neuropsychology usually comes in a fragmented way&lt;/strong&gt;, little by little. &lt;em&gt;A bit of cognitive neuroscience here, a bit of neuropsychological syndromes there, some cognitive tests administration over here, and some cortical neuroanatomy over there&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; Though we might, &lt;em&gt;in fine&lt;/em&gt;, acquire a global vision and understanding of neuropsychology, verbalizing it is seldom necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The definition of neuropsychology is actually quite complex to formalize, and can even be hotly debated. The jobs and positions that stem out of this field are many, and &lt;strong&gt;practitioners often tend to circumscribe neuropsychology to their own activity&lt;/strong&gt;. For instance, a neuropsychologist that mainly does cognitive rehabilitation with psychiatric patients might have quite a different vision from another that does, day after day, presurgical cognitive assessments. And that is without mentioning the neuropsychologists pursuing an academic career, or even the ones that have moved to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No problem&lt;/em&gt;, would argue the careful reader, &lt;em&gt;if the definitions are too narrow, let&amp;rsquo;s take more general one&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not that simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Indeed, neuropsychology occupies a very particular place in the network of science, as it is at &lt;strong&gt;the crossroads between social sciences, biological sciences and medical fields&lt;/strong&gt;. Giving a definition that is too large would lose its essence in the nebulous depths of neuroscience and psychology, which would be not be accurate; neuropsychologists, whether they are clinical practitioners or not, have a common training, a specific theoretical grounding, as well as a unique interpretation and analysis framework underpinned by a scientifically rigorous method. Taking these elements into account, I will attempt to give a &lt;strong&gt;simple, comprehensive and informative definition of neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first axiom that we need to discuss is the notion of science. &lt;strong&gt;Is neuropsychology its &amp;ldquo;own&amp;rdquo; scientific field&lt;/strong&gt;, or is it a mere portion of another one, such as cognitive neuroscience or psychology, which differs from other specializations only through its object of interest? &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;By science&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, says Schopenhauer in his PhD thesis with a baroque title (On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason), &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;we understand a system of notions, i.e. a totality of connected, as opposed to a mere aggregate of disconnected, notions.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; This definition applies well to neuropsychology, that contains a set of theories, hypotheses, methods and proofs feeding from one another and creating a coherent ensemble. As such, neuropsychology is its own scientific discipline, although a singular one&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, &lt;strong&gt;what is the &amp;ldquo;bigger&amp;rdquo; box in which neuropsychology fits?&lt;/strong&gt; While neuropsychologists are often initially trained in psychology, one could argue that the focus on the brain makes it more belonging to neuroscience. Well, the organization and structure of Science is a complicated issue. However, the particularity of the topographical location of neuropsychology is quite apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, neuropsychology belongs to a cluster of sciences interested a specific biological organ: the brain. As such, &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology is an integral part of neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt;. On the other hand, neuropsychology is interested in the productions of the brain (e.g., thoughts, feelings and behaviours) with a focus on the cognitive level (analyzing things in terms of cognitive processes and mechanisms), which makes it also &lt;strong&gt;belonging to psychology&lt;/strong&gt;. Moreover, one could argue that neuropsychology, through its integration of the study of what we are biologically, and who we are mentally, has been connected to, and used as evidence in, &lt;strong&gt;philosophy of mind&lt;/strong&gt; debates (for instance, famous neuropsychological cases studied by Sacks, Ramachandran or Milner have been widely discussed by contemporary philosophers). Finally, contrary to many other domains, neuropsychology has also an applied, practical component, that can be used in clinical practice. This clinical aspect, registering &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology withing medical fields&lt;/strong&gt;, takes multiple forms, such as assessment, diagnostic or therapeutic care, and can be used with a wide variety of patients and illnesses. These multiple facets make the wealth of &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology, which offers an exceptional freedom of practice&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we have seen, &lt;strong&gt;neuropsychology is located at the centre of colliding galaxies of knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;, such as neuroscience, psychology, medicine and philosophy. However, the fast development of neuropsychology is gradually leading to the creation of subcomponents within itself, corresponding to different practices and theoretical steps. And these clusters are themselves growing. For instance, clinical neuropsychology was historically focused on diagnostic cognitive assessments, but has recently expanded on the treatment-side of things, with innovations like cognitive training and rehabilitation. This underlines neuropsychology as a rapidly evolving field, moving its potential towards yet uncharted territories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourfold-structure-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The fourfold structure of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuropsychology is born from the convergence of &lt;strong&gt;cognitive neurology&lt;/strong&gt;, with pioneers such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Broca&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Broca&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Wernicke&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wernicke&lt;/a&gt; (which made inferences about brain functioning based on the observations of patients with brain lesions) and psychologists such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Th%C3%A9odule-Armand_Ribot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ribot&lt;/a&gt; (focusing on the organization and semiology of cognitive deficits). This history has shaped neuropsychology as a two-faced entity, with one &lt;strong&gt;experimental side&lt;/strong&gt; dedicated to understand the relationship between brain and cognition (by using pathological cases or natural variability of neurocognitive characteristics), and one &lt;strong&gt;clinical aspect&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on bringing this knowledge to the benefit of the patients suffering from brain disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, beyond these two pillars of neuropsychology, recent advances have outlined a more &lt;strong&gt;theoretical level&lt;/strong&gt; of neuropsychology, dedicated to a high-level integration of the data at hand to elaborate general theories and interfacing them with evolutionary or philosophical principles. Similarly, a &lt;strong&gt;computational&lt;/strong&gt; facet, referring to the operationalization of the functioning in statistical terms, starts to emerge as a pseudo-independent aspect, propelled by the regain of interest and focus on the methodological and statistical aspects of psychology and neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This structure is not fixed, but driven by the evolution of the field. It is possible that new poles will emerge, or differentiate over time, until maybe they separate from - or create new clusters within - neuropsychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;cycle.png&#34; alt=&#34;Structure of neuropsychology&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The fourfold structure of neuropsychology.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-definition-of-neuropsychology&#34;&gt;The definition of neuropsychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neuropsychology is a theoretical and practical science investigating the relationship between 1) the structure and functioning of the brain, and 2) cognitive processes and their related derivatives, such as thoughts, feelings and behaviours.&lt;/strong&gt; It is organised in four interconnected and overlapping dimensions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; studies the variability of the brain and cognition (whether from pathological origin or not) to test theories and models through empirical experimentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clinical neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; uses theories and models about mental functioning to better detect and assess disorders and deficits, leading to a precise diagnostic and an adapted treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computational neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; transforms the data acquired through experiments and observation into logical or statistical models of mental functioning that are used to operationalize the processes at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theoretical neuropsychology&lt;/strong&gt; integrates the evidence to elaborate and develop unifying theories to address fundamental questions about mental functioning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neuropsychology is located at the crossroads between neuroscience and psychology, at the interface between theory and practice. &lt;strong&gt;Its practitioners, the neuropsychologists&lt;/strong&gt;, are bound by a specific training, by unique theoretical and historical references, and are endowed with an analysis and interpretation framework backed by a rigorous and scientific investigation methodology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie expérimentale étudie les variabilités du cerveau et de la cognition (qu’elles soient d’origine pathologique ou non) pour tester des modèles et développer des théories sur le fonctionnement mental, visant ainsi à une meilleure compréhension de l’Homme. --&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie clinique utilise les théories et les modèles sur le fonctionnement mental pour mieux détecter et appréhender les troubles et les déficits d’une pathologie, menant à un diagnostic précis, tout en développant et appliquant des prises en charges modernes et adaptées. --&gt;
&lt;!-- La neuropsychologie se situe au centre de la nébuleuse des neurosciences, au carrefour de la théorie et de la pratique. Ses praticiens, les neuropsychologues, sont liés par une formation commune, des bases théoriques spécifiques, un canevas d’analyse et d’interprétation sous-tendu par une méthode d’investigation rigoureuse et scientifique.  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks for reading! Do not hesitate to tweet and share this post, and leave a comment below&lt;/em&gt; 🤗&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nicolas, S., &amp;amp; Murray, D. J. (1999). Théodule Ribot (1839–1916), founder of French psychology: A biographical introduction. History of Psychology, 2(4), 277.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Schopenhauer, A. (1813). &lt;em&gt;On the Fourfold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason&lt;/em&gt;. PhD dissertation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;You can reference this post as follows:&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;- Makowski, D. (2020, September 13). What is Neuropsychology?. Retrieved from &lt;a href=&#34;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/what_is_neuropsychology/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/post/what_is_neuropsychology/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive Control</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/cognitivecontrol/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/cognitivecontrol/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuropsydia</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/neuropsydia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/neuropsydia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Patient Assessment</title>
      <link>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/patientassessmentapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://dominiquemakowski.github.io/project/patientassessmentapp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
